<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The judgment of the foreign reformed churches concerning the rites and offices of the Church of England shewing there is no necessity of alterations : in a letter to a member of the House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Willes, John, 1646 or 7-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8187</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12529516</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12529516</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62742</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62742)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 952:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The judgment of the foreign reformed churches concerning the rites and offices of the Church of England shewing there is no necessity of alterations : in a letter to a member of the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Willes, John, 1646 or 7-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Jenkinson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Willis. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [6]-[7]</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62742:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62742:1"/>
            <p>THE JUDGMENT OF THE Foreign Reformed Churches CONCERNING THE RITES and OFFICES OF THE <hi>Church of England:</hi> SHEWING There is no neceſſity of Alterations. In a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a Member of the <hi>Houſe of Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bramhill's</hi> Works, <hi>p. 494. All Proteſtants both</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans <hi>and</hi> Calviniſts <hi>did give unto the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Church the Right Hand of Fellowſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſaubon's</hi> Prayer, <hi>A. D. 1610. Thou, O Lord Jeſus, preſerve the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and give a ſound mind to the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts, who deride its Rites and Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Jenkinſon,</hi> A. D. 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62742:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62742:2"/>
            <head>To the Honoured <hi>A. A.</hi> A MEMBER Of the Honourable HOUSE of COMMONS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEN we parted at the Election, you deſired me to give you the Judgment of the Foreign Proteſtants about the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and particularly as to the Rites and Offices, of which the Author of the Letter to the Convocation tells us, p.</hi> 23. That if the Convocation do not alter them, moſt certainly the Parliament will. <hi>The very talk of Change, you know, breeds a Ferment in the Nation, and be ſure the diſcontented will make their advantage of it; but if the Nation finds the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ſteddy as the Convocation, the Heats will ſoon be over, and the Kingdom return to her Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Peace.</hi> Nolumus leges Angliae mutare, <hi>was an Anſwer firſt in Parliament, and that in oppoſition to ſome Eccleſiaſticks, who would have introduced ſeveral Foreign Rites and Cuſtoms, into the room of received</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:62742:3"/> and approved Conſtitutions, <hi>quae huc uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> uſitatae ſunt ac approbatae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Optatus Milev. l. 3. p. 75.</hi> tells us of his time, <hi>That there had been a Report ſpread by ſome that came from the Emperor, that Alterations ſhould be made in the Liturgy, which ſtartled the People; but when they ſaw their Solemn Cuſtoms and wonted Rites obſerved, and that nothing was changed, added, or diminiſh'd in their Divine Service, they were quieted again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe Governments have been obſerved to continue longeſt that have been moſt ſteddy in their Laws; and the Jews who were immediately governed by God, had their very Rites and Ceremonies unaltered for almoſt 2000 Years, their great Law-giver foreſeeing, that every conſiderable Alteration in an eſtabliſh'd Religion, or even its Rites and Modes, would put the State into Convulſions, and indanger a Revolution.</p>
            <p>As to our preſent Conjuncture, it was a great over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in thoſe that carryed on the Deſign of a Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to begin with a Toleration; and its unreaſonable to think that the Diſſenters will unite with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, ſo long as their Separation is allowed. Nothing that you can do, will promote their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, but that which makes it their Intereſt, and that can be only done by Rewards and Puniſhments; and therefore the taking off the Sanctions of the Laws, and making the Separation eaſie, was beginning at the wrong end, and a certain way to make a Comprehenſion ineffectual.</p>
            <p>But ſince the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion propoſed is not confined to our Nation, but extended to all the Proteſtants in the World, that are now united in their Intereſts; I have here,
<pb facs="tcp:62742:3"/> according to your Deſires, given you a true account of the great eſteem and veneration they all have for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and particularly for thoſe very Rites and Cuſtoms that are now diſputed, and what Offence and Scandal our Diſſenters give them; ſo that by an impartial Conſideration of their Opinions, you, and all the Nation may be ſatisfied that making of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations in the Inſtances propoſed, will be ſo far from promoting a cloſer <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with the Foreign Proteſtants, (who have always eſteemed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, as the very <hi>Center of Union,)</hi> that its the moſt certain way to hinder it.</p>
            <p>For what concerns the late Convocation, I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to an excellent Paper, Entituled, <hi>Remarks from the Country upon the Two Letters relating to the Convocation and Alterations in the Liturgy,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>I am Your moſt Humble Servant, N. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:62742:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. THE <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the Church of <hi>England</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly <hi>appeal to the Foreign Proteſtant Churches,</hi> as Perſons of <hi>their Opinions. p. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Some Inconſiderate or Deſigning Perſons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have joyned with them in this Appeal and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint. <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4, 5.</item>
               <item>3. This Opinion Confuted in general. <hi>p.</hi> 6, 7.</item>
               <item>4. The Opinions of <hi>Beza, Spanheim, Diodate, Caſaubon, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chart, Dumoulin,</hi> &amp;c. concerning the <hi>Church of</hi> England <hi>Eſtabliſhed. p.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</item>
               <item>5. The Opinion that the Foreign Reformed Divines have of our Diſſenters, particularly the Opinion of <hi>Calvin, Beza, Gualter, Caſaubon, Bochart, Capellus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 12, 13, 14.</item>
               <item>6. Theſe General Opinions applyed to the Matters propoſed to be Altered by the Authors of the <hi>Letters</hi> to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,</hi> and in behalf of the <hi>Bill</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the <hi>Foreign Proteſtants,</hi> is ſhewed as to Reading the Apocryphal Books in the Church. <hi>p.</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17, 19, 20, 21.</item>
               <item>7. As to the Rules for finding <hi>Eaſter. p</hi> 22, 23, 24, 25.</item>
               <item>8. As to the Names of ſome old Saints and Biſhops in the Kalendar. <hi>p.</hi> 25, 26.</item>
               <item>9. As to the Reading the old Verſion of the Pſalms. <hi>p.</hi> 26. 27, 28, 29, 30, 31.</item>
               <item>10. As to the retaining the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed. <hi>p.</hi> 32, 33.</item>
               <item>11. As to the Croſs in Baptiſm. <hi>p.</hi> 34.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:62742:4"/>
               <item>12. As to Godfathers in Baptiſm. <hi>p.</hi> 35, 36.</item>
               <item>13. As to Kneeling at the Sacrament. <hi>p.</hi> 37, 38.</item>
               <item>14. As to Excommunication for Contempt. <hi>p.</hi> 41.</item>
               <item>15. As to Ordination by Biſhops only. <hi>p.</hi> 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49, 50, 51, 52.</item>
               <item>16. As to Set Forms of Prayers. <hi>p.</hi> 53, 54.</item>
               <item>17. As to Eſtabliſhed Rites and Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 55, 56, 57.</item>
               <item>18. One Word to the Diſſenters. <hi>p.</hi> 58. 59.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:62742:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 6. l. 24. <hi>Humphred</hi> read <hi>Humphrys,</hi> p. 17. l. 27. <hi>Populare</hi> read <hi>Populari,</hi> p. 20. l. 2. <hi>Polyglot Latin,</hi> read <hi>Polyglot Bible,</hi> p. 22. l. 35. <hi>Venral</hi> read <hi>Vernal,</hi> p. 26. l. 18. <hi>Eviſpine</hi> read <hi>Criſpine,</hi> p. 31. l. 24. <hi>perpagato</hi> read <hi>propagato,</hi> p. 43. l. 34. <hi>pretented</hi> read <hi>pretenſed.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62742:5"/>
            <head>THE JUDGMENT OF THE Foreign Reformed Churches CONCERNING THE RITES and OFFICES OF THE <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THERE have been Three Reaſons much ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of late for making Alterations in the Rites and Offices of the Church of <hi>England</hi> at this Juncture; the <hi>1ſt</hi> relates to our ſelves, the <hi>2d</hi> to Diſſenters, and the <hi>3d</hi> to Foreign Churches. To the <hi>1ſt</hi> it hath been anſwered, that we do not need Alterations; to the <hi>2d</hi> that they do not deſire them; and the <hi>3d</hi> is the Subject of this Diſcourſe. And though the Learned Books of <hi>Durel, Comber, Falkner</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62742:6"/> might have rendered ſuch a deſign needleſs, yet ſo long as the Adverſaries of our Peace and Eſtabliſhment go on to amuſe the Nation with old Fictions and Stories, we muſt not ceaſe to repeat old truths and plain matter of fact to confute them, not doubting but that as truth is great, ſo it will prevail.</p>
            <p>It hath been the conſtant practice of the Preshyterian Party to boaſt of their Harmony and Agreement with the Foreign Reformed Churches, in thoſe things wherein they differ from us, and frequently inſinuate to their Followers, that the Proteſtants abroad were much offended with the Rites and Offices of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Thus their great Founder <hi>T. C.</hi> in his Preface to the Admonition. <hi>Out of the Realm they have all the beſt Reformed Churches in</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom <hi>againſt them;</hi> i. e. The Presbyterians againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi> In his Admonition, he frequently appeals to the beſt Reformed Churches, and particularly <hi>p. 286. Our Ordination by Biſhops is ſtrange from the uſe of all well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches in the World.</hi> In the Solemn League and Covenant, they all Swore, <hi>To endeavour the Reformation of Religion, according to the Example of the beſt Reformed Churches.</hi> Ordinance of Parliament, for taking away the Common-Prayer, <hi>Jan. 3d, 1644.—Reſolving to Reform Religion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Example of the beſt Reformed Churches.</hi> Preface to the Directory; <hi>The Liturgy of the Church of</hi> England <hi>hath proved an Offence to the Reformed Churches abroad.—That we may anſwer the expectation of other reformed Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Presbyterians aſſembled at the <hi>Savoy</hi> in the Year 1660, declare, <hi>That in the Liturgy are things that have given offence to Learned and Judicious Drvines of other Reformed Churches.</hi> In their Petition for Peace, p. 9. <hi>And if you ſhould reject (which God forbid) the moderate Propoſals which now and formerly we have made, we offer to your conſideration, what judgment all the Proteſtant Churches are likely to paſs on your Proceedings.</hi> And again, <hi>p. 10; How ſtrange muſt it needs ſeem to the Reformed Churhes, to the whole Chriſtian World,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>p. 13. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the moſt Reformed Churches take this Conformity to be</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62742:6"/> 
               <hi>Sin.</hi> And after this manner they declare all the World on their ſide, and that the Foreign Churches admire at the ſtiffneſs of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by which contrivance though never ſo falſe, they raiſe the heats and clamours of the ignorant and unthinking part of the Nation againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And ſtill they go on to clamour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us without any proof, though they have been ſo often urged to it; and I here challenge them all to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any one Authentick Act of any National Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church in the World, which hath at the leaſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon, or Cenſured the Eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet all this, however vile and baſe, is no more than we might juſtly have expected from the Profeſſed Enemies of our Peace and Eſtabliſhment; but that which raiſed the admiration and aſtoniſhment of all Sober Men, was to ſee the Profeſſed Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Men of Rank and Dignity, embark'd in the ſame bottom of miſtake and error, and purſuing the ſame hideous outcries againſt us; a miſtake they could not run into, but for want of good Books or good Company, which would have informed them better, and too much conſining their Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and their Converſations to that ill ſort of Men. So that now our Church may juſtly take up the complaint of <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm 55. 12, 14, 15. <hi>It is not an open Enemy that hath done me this diſhonour, for then I could have born it;—but it was even thou my Companion, my Guide, and mine own Familiar Friend: We took ſweet Counſel together, and walked in the Houſe of God as Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this ſort is the Diſcourſe concerning the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Commiſſion, <hi>p. 24. The Eyes of all the World be open upon us, all the Reformed Churches are in expectation of ſomething to be done which makes for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Peace.</hi> And a Letter to a Member of Parliament in favour of the Bill for a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Union, <hi>p. 5; For them that have not Epiſcopal Orders, there will be ſuch a proviſion made, as will ſatisfie all the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Foreign Proteſtant Churches.</hi> Again <hi>p. 6. And for</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62742:7"/> French <hi>and</hi> German, <hi>and other Foreign Chriſtians of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, I am well aſſured by Letters ſent from</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Geneva, Switzerland, <hi>and other Places (not to ſpeak of the Churches of the</hi> Lutheran <hi>Communion which write the ſame) that they eſteem the Conditions propoſed in this Bill, (which hath been communicated to them) as Terms fit for uniting of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</hi> Where by the way, I cannot but admire at the ſpeed and diligence of this Perſons Correſpondence; the King had not accepted of the Government till <hi>February,</hi> after this the Convention is declared a Parliament; and then after ſome more neceſſary things for ſetling the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, a project is ſet on work for a Bill of Union, and yet he had ſent a Copy of the Contents of it to <hi>Germany, Holland, Geneva, Switzerland,</hi> &amp;c. and received their ſeveral Approbations of it in <hi>March,</hi> for that Paper is Licenſed <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril 1ſt.</hi> And yet it's more ſtrange, that even the Churches of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Communion ſhould approve the conditions of that Bill of Union: It was not long before, that an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Author of undoubted credit; gave us an authentick account of a Letter from ſeveral Miniſters in <hi>Germany, That the greateſt part of the Proteſtants of</hi> Europe <hi>have been extreamly ſcandalized at our Diſſenters,—That the Diſſenters ought by no means to have ſeparated themſelves for the form of Eccleſiaſtical Government, nor for Ceremonies;—That the Biſhops have juſtified themſelves from the reproach of being Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected, and of Perſecuting the Diſſenters; they have made it appear that they were only Calumnies invented by their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to render them odious to Proteſtants;—How much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter would it be for the Diſſenters to re-unite themſelves to the Biſhops, with whom they differ only in ſome Points of Diſcipline?</hi> And now quite contrary, all the Reformed Churches ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that we ſhould comply, and unite with the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>But without croſſing the Seas, we may make a fair gueſs at the incredibility of all this Foreign Account, by the very next Pretence, which gives as ſtrange an Account of our ſelves at Home. <hi>I am not ſingular in this, for amongſt all thoſe who have appeared in the Churches cauſe, as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62742:7"/> Diſſenters as Papists; I do not know one ſingle Perſon that is not a well-wiſher to this Bill, and I believe they will all tell you ſo.</hi> The direct contrary being manifeſtly true, not only in ſeveral of the Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſioners who were call'd together to conſult of that matter, but alſo in the far greater part of the whole Convocation. And if that Author be miſtaken in the Age he lives in, we have great hopes to think he is as much miſtaken in the Ages paſt, for ſo it follows, <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> Uſher, <hi>Biſhop</hi> Sanderſon, <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond, <hi>and a long Order of other moſt Worthy Men of the laſt Age, whoſe Memory is moſt precious in our Church, had they been now alive, would with all Zeal have promoted this Bill of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> Which very Paragraph is the reverſe of one of Mr. <hi>Baxters,</hi> in his Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet—I am paſt doubt that</hi> Richard Hooker, <hi>Biſhop</hi> Bilſon, <hi>Biſhop</hi> Uſher, <hi>and ſuch others, were they now alive, would be Nonconformiſts, yea, I can prove it, &amp;c.</hi> and if ſo, they would not be for the Bill of Union, which hath been generally oppoſed by the Nonconformiſts. The Preface to the Directory runs in the ſame Style. <hi>We have no inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to diſparage our firſt Reformers, of whom we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that were they now alive, they would joyn with us in this Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus its evident that theſe Sons of Comprehenſion joyn with the Diſſenters, to cry it up, that all the World is on their ſide, and clamour againſt all that oppoſe them, as the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> did againſt the Apoſtles, <hi>Act. 17. 6. Theſe Men would turn the World up-ſide down;</hi> whenas their deſpiſing of us, and magnifying of the Foreign Churches, is like that which <hi>OEcolampadius</hi> tells us in his Epiſtles, p. 177. <hi>Aliis</hi> OEcolampadius, <hi>aliis</hi> Zuinglius <hi>ſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, atqui nos amici ſumus &amp; fuimus ſemper, &amp; nemo grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatur nobis qui propter nos diſſidium ſeminat,</hi> i. e. <hi>Some deſpiſe</hi> OEcolampadius, <hi>and ſome</hi> Zuinglius, <hi>but we are, and always were Friends, nor doth any one pleaſe us that ſowes Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord upon our Accounts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62742:8"/>
            <p>Let us therefore take a ſhort view of the judgment of the Foreign Divines, and ſee what Opinion they have of this ſtiff, vile, ſinful Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Reformation in general conſiſts of Lutherans and Calviniſts, ſo I find that agreement betwixt them in the moſt material Things; as that <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf ſubſcribed the Lutheran Confeſſion of <hi>Ausburgh,</hi> and a whole Synod of his Diſciples at <hi>Charenton</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> in the Year 1631. declared, <hi>That there was no Idolatry nor Superſtition in the Lutheran Churches, and therefore the Members of their Churches might be received into Communion with them, without renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their Opinions or their Practices;</hi> ſo that, tho Papiſts and indiſcreet Fanaticks have endeavour'd to ſet theſe two great parts of the Reformation as far aſunder as poſſible; yet the more ſober Proteſtants have thought them very reconcilable, and always endeavour'd it. Now the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been Eſtabliſh'd in a middle way, betwixt both extreams, and laid aſide thoſe things which on either hand gave the greateſt Offence; by which means our Eſtabliſh'd Church hath been look'd upon by mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Men, as the very Center of Union and Harmony of all the Proteſtant Churches in the World. For this very reaſon when <hi>Calvin</hi> offer'd his Aſſiſtance to Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> he was refuſed by him. The Famous Dr. <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frede,</hi> who was one of thoſe Learned Men that fled abroad in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Reign, in his <hi>Prax. Cur. Rom. p.</hi> 70. tells us, <hi>Nos non ſumus Calviniani, nec Reformationem noſtram Calviniſmum dicimus, We are not Calviniſts in</hi> England, <hi>nor do we call our Reformation Calviniſm;</hi> and yet this was the Religion eſtabliſh'd by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when that great Man wrote; and Sir <hi>Edwin Sandys</hi> who had made a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſurvey of all the Religions in <hi>Europe,</hi> ſaith expreſly, p. 214. <hi>That no</hi> Luther, <hi>no</hi> Calvin <hi>was the Square of our Faith.</hi> Now for our Church thus happily eſtabliſh'd, to alter to either extream, is ſo far from promoting the Union of the Reformed Churches, that its the moſt likely way to hinder it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62742:8"/>
            <p>If we look upon the Lutheran Churches, they have either Biſhops; as <hi>Denmark, Norway</hi> and <hi>Swedland,</hi> or elſe Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendants, (which is another Name for Biſhops) who have power of Ordination and Juriſdiction, as our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in <hi>England.</hi> They have all ſet Liturgies and Forms of Prayer, they obſerve Holy-days and ſet-Faſts, have Organs, Hymns and Anthems; they wear Surplices; uſe the Croſs in Baptiſm; receive the Communion kneeling, and make uſe of all thoſe Rites which have been objected againſt the Church of <hi>England;</hi> ſo that to alter theſe, muſt needs give Offence to all thoſe Churches, and ſet us at a greater diſtance from them. And as theſe Alterations propoſed, can never tend to an Union among Proteſtants, ſo they muſt needs look ill at this time, when not only all theſe Churches are united to us in one common Alliance for the defence of our Religion, but alſo the very next Branch of our Royal Family is ſo nearly related to them.</p>
            <p>As for ſuch as propoſe our Union with the reformed Churches of <hi>France, Geneva</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> let them conſider that the firſt of theſe is not, and ſo we have now leſs reaſon than formerly; the ſecond is only a particular City, (for the Swiſs are generally Lutherans,) and its a very unreaſonable Project of Union, to have three Kingdoms alter their Religion for conformity with one City; when at the ſame time they ſet themſelves at a greater Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with ſo many Kingdoms of the Reformed Religion. As for <hi>Holland,</hi> its well known that they allow of all ſorts of Religions, and its impoſſible that any ſetled Uniformity amongſt our ſelves can ever bring us to an Union to ſuch a mixture and variety. The Chriſtian Religion was firſt planted among them by an Engliſh Biſhop, and our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was fix'd and ſetled here before theirs began.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Diſſenters boaſt that the Reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways on their ſide, and joyn'd with them in their abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> I will next conſider what Opinion the Learned Men, even of thoſe Churches, have had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62742:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> of ours. Firſt, for <hi>Geneva.</hi> And for his Learning and Eminency, I will begin with the Famous</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Beza,</hi> Who in his Letter to Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> hath theſe Words, <hi>The Engliſh Church is the Harbour of all the Godly, and the Preſerver of all other Reformed Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Spanheim,</hi> Profeſſor there, in his Epiſtle to Arch-Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> and others. <hi>I often call to mind thoſe Fortunate Iſles of yours—That Beauteous Face of your Church—That Reverence in the Publick Worſhip of God—The Church of</hi> Geneva <hi>hath a great affection to the Britiſh Churches, whoſe Biſhops we admire; for whoſe Proſperity we daily Pray, that your Church may continue to praiſe God as it doth; that the Biſhops may continue in their Authority, and your Church in Peace,</hi> &amp;c. and this was Written <hi>A. D.</hi> 1638. Then for his Succeſſor</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>John Diodate,</hi> Profeſſor at <hi>Geneva,</hi> in his Anſwer to the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> when they had deſired his Opinion about their Proceedings. <hi>England</hi> (in the time of its Epiſcopacy) <hi>was the very Eye and Excellency of all Churches, Chriſts own choice and peculiar—What a ſad Spectacle is it to ſee that Church trodden under Feet—An horrid thing</hi> (that you have done) <hi>and never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heard of amongſt the Reformed Churches—We are ſtruck with Horrour at the change of the glorious Face of that Church; may God reſtore your Churches to that high Eſtate, and pitch of Holineſs and Glory in which they have hitherto excell'd and out-ſhin'd all the Churches upon the Earth.</hi> And this is the eſteem <hi>Geneva</hi> had for the Epiſcopal Church of <hi>England,</hi> and certainly we ought not to alter the beſt Church in the World, to comply with that, which by their Confeſſion is not ſo good.</p>
            <p>In the next place let us ſee the French Divines, I will begin 1. with <hi>Caſaubon,</hi> in his Epiſtle to King <hi>James</hi> the I. <hi>The Church of</hi> England <hi>comes nearer the form of the flouriſhing Chriſtian Church of old, than any other; it hath taken a middle way betwixt thoſe Churches which are amiſs, either through ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs or defect—If my Judgment doth not deceive me, the moſt ſound part of the whole Reformation is in</hi> England.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62742:9"/>2. The learned <hi>Bochart,</hi> in his Epiſtle to Biſhop <hi>Morley. There are none, of the reformed of</hi> France, <hi>if they happen to be in</hi> England, <hi>but willingly joyn with the Church of</hi> England <hi>as by Law eſtabliſh'd; and as ſoon as they can get a competent knowledge of the Engliſh Tongue, are preſent at her Offices, and receive the Holy Communion there, which I have often my ſelf done at</hi> London <hi>and at</hi> Oxford: <hi>This is not only my. Opinion, but of all the Paſtors of the Reformed Religion in</hi> France.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Peter du Moulin</hi> in the Preface to his Fathers Anſwer to <hi>Perron, The Church of</hi> England <hi>hath more of the Primitive and Apoſtolick Church-Government than any other Church in the reſt of the world.—The French Proteſtants have the ſame good Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of it, and deſire to enjoy the ſame Government, if they might be ſo happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Monſieur <hi>Claude</hi> in his Letter publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet. The Church of</hi> France <hi>hath always looked upon and conſidered the Church of</hi> England <hi>not only as a Siſter, but an elder Siſter, for which we have a reſpect and veneration, and daily pray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Monſiur <hi>Le Moyne</hi> in a Letter publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet, All the Proteſtants of</hi> France, Geneva, Switzerland, Germany <hi>and</hi> Holland, <hi>look upon the Church of</hi> England <hi>as a very Orthodox Church;—All the Proteſtant Churches have always had a very great reſpect for the Purity of the Church of</hi> England. And in another Letter to Dr. <hi>Brevint,</hi> publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Durell, I praiſe God for our Reformation in</hi> France, <hi>but I fear not to ſay, that if we had kept Biſhops, and as many Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies as would ſerve to fix the Attention of the People without Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, we ſhould have ſeen for certain far greater progreſs of the Reformation.</hi> To which I cannot but add what Monſieur <hi>Ronee</hi> a French Embaſſador in <hi>England,</hi> when he ſaw our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Services and Rites, told King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, <hi>That if the Reformed Church of</hi> France <hi>had kept the ſame Order among them which we have, he was aſſured that there would have been many thouſands of Proteſtants more than now there are.</hi> And this Obſervation is ſo undoubtedly true, that it long ſince forc'd this Expreſſion from one of our bitter Enemies, <hi>Sanders de Schiſm. Angl.</hi> p. 283. <hi>Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>in her Reformation kept many of the Rites and Manners of the ancient Church, which</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:62742:10"/> 
               <hi>very much conduced to the Firmneſs and Eſtabliſhment of her He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſio; for had things been left to the capriciouſneſs of ſome of the new Clergy that talk'd much of the Goſpel-Liberty, it had all long ſince vaniſh'd into Smoke, but by her Polity was ſtrengthned and ſupported.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Monſieur <hi>De L' Angle</hi> in his Letter publiſh'd by Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet,</hi> p. 421. <hi>I am ſure with what an exceeding Joy the Proteſtant Churches of</hi> France <hi>would enter into Communion with you (i. e.</hi> the Church of <hi>England)</hi> And in his Letter to <hi>Durel,</hi> publiſhed by him, <hi>p. 70, 71. I rejoyced very much at the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the</hi> Anglico-Gallicane Church, <hi>(i. e.</hi> the French Church, with the Engliſh Common-Prayer and Rites) <hi>that this may make known to the World the Communion that is betwixt us, and that the Reformed Churches of</hi> France <hi>have not that averſion againſt the Diſcipline of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>which ſome Men report they have; I am certain my Collegues are of the ſame mind with me.</hi> And again, <hi>p. 143. My Heart did leap for joy when I heard that your Liturgy and ancient Diſcipline was reſtored, i. e.</hi> in the year 1660.</p>
            <p>To theſe Teſtimonies I will add the Obſervation of <hi>Dur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> a French-man alſo, <hi>p. 92. When the French Church in</hi> London <hi>was eſtabliſh'd with the Engliſh Liturgy and Rites, tho Providence brought over many Miniſters from beyond the Seas, ſome from</hi> Geneva, <hi>ſome from</hi> France, <hi>ſome from</hi> Germany, <hi>ſome from</hi> Poland, <hi>ſome from</hi> Lithuania, <hi>ſome from</hi> Piemont, <hi>and almoſt from all the Reformed Churches, we have ſeen none of them, that made any difficulty to aſſiſt at Divine Service, and conform; all of them received the Sacrament kneeling,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And I cannot but wonder with what Face the Men of this Age preſs us to make Alterations for the ſake of other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, when we ſee thoſe of the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of <hi>France,</hi> who are all <hi>Calvinists,</hi> and who out of Zeal to God's Glory, readily ſacrificed all their Secular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to their Religion, and come over to this Kingdom, have univerſally joyn'd with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in her Liturgy and Rites, received the Lords Supper on their Knees, had their Children Baptized with Godfathers, and ſigned with the Sign of the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all this at a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62742:10"/> time when the Laws of this Kingdom gave them Liberty to joyn with what Communion they pleaſed. Which was ſuch an unanſwerable Argument to our Diſſenters, God having as it were brought a Nation from another Kingdom to convince them, that it was generally obſerved through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Kingdom, that the Diſſenters were very cold in their Charity towards them.</p>
            <p>If we look into the Churches of <hi>Holland,</hi> 'tis true all ſorts of Religions are allowed; but it's evident that the great and Leading Men there have ever had a great Eſteem for the Church of <hi>England;</hi> witneſs the great Reſpect and Honour they had for the Engliſh Biſhops in the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> when they neither had nor deſired any Repreſentatives from our Presbyterians: Witneſs the two Famous <hi>Voſſius's,</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son, who always ſpoke with all Reſpect and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo far approved of our Cathedral Service, as that the Father was Prebendary of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Son Prebendary of <hi>Windſor.</hi> Witneſs the Famous <hi>Grotius,</hi> who always admired the Church of <hi>England</hi> above all the Churches in the World, and upon his Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed recommended it to his Wife, and ſuch others of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily that were then about him, obliging them to adhere firmly to it, which was readily obeyed by them. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall'<hi>s Vind. of</hi> Grotius, cap. 2. Witneſs the two <hi>Junius</hi>'s and many others; but I ſhall only add the preſent Famous, Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inſtance, his preſent Majeſty King <hi>William,</hi> who was born and always bred in that Church, and yet from his firſt coming into <hi>England,</hi> hath readily and conſtantly joyned with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> uſed her Liturgy with great Devotion and Honour, and obſerv'd all its Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, as Kneeling, Standing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in their proper places, and upon all occaſions, hath declared himſelf zealouſly and heartily in her Praiſe and Commendations, and promiſed his Protection of it, and all this at ſuch times, when the contrary Intereſt wasmoſt prevalent, and he was daily beſet with thoſe that were no Friends to the preſent Eſtabliſhment. All which is an undeniable Argument how readily thoſe of <hi>Holland</hi> would joyn with us.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62742:11"/>
            <p>As to the Northern Churches, we have a great Example before us in the Prince of <hi>Denmark.</hi> And laſtly, For the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> not to mention the ſeveral Synods and Acts of Parliament by which Biſhops, ſet forms of Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have been eſtabliſhed amongſt them, and the ſame Rites as are in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Not to mention the great number amongſt them that at this time are vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Aſſerters of Epiſcopacy; Let King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt ſpeak for all, in his Speech delivered in the Star-Chamber, <hi>An. Dom. 1616.—I ſay in my Conſcience, that the Church of</hi> England, <hi>of any Church that ever I read or knew of, preſent or paſt, is moſt pure and neareſt the Primitive and Apoſtolick Church, in Doctrine and Diſcipline, and is ſurelieſt founded upon the Word of God, of any Church in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And having thus far ſeen the great Eſteem the Reformed Churches abroad have for the Church of <hi>England</hi> as by Law eſtabliſhed, let us next fee what Opinion they have of the Presbyterians, and other Diſſenters amongſt us.</p>
            <p>I will begin with <hi>Calvin,</hi> who in his Book <hi>De Neceſſ. Ref. Eccl.</hi> ſaith, <hi>If any be found that do not reverence ſuch an Hierarchy, (i. e.</hi> ſuch as we have in <hi>England) and ſubject themſelves to the ſame with the loweſt Obedience, I confeſs there is no Anathema whereof he is not worthy.</hi> And again, <hi>In a well-ſetled Church, diverſities of Cuſtoms is not to be ſuffered.</hi> Next for <hi>Beza</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Engliſh Puritans from <hi>Geneva, A. D. 1567. (of his Epiſtles,</hi> p. 97.) <hi>I tremble to think that any ſhould perform their Miniſterial Duty againſt the Will of her Majeſty and the Biſhops.</hi> And in another Epiſtle to Archbiſhop <hi>Grindon, A. D.</hi> 1566. ſpeaking of the ſame Perſons, <hi>Its in vain for them to pretend weakneſs in a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where the Goſpel hath been preach'd ſo many years, and been confirmed with the Blood of ſo many Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62742:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Gualterus</hi> in his Epiſtle Dedicatory of his Homilies upon the <hi>1ſt</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> calls thoſe <hi>moroſe</hi> and <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,</hi> who for things indifferent trouble the peace of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſeparate from her Communion,—<hi>Who whilſt they endeavour to reduce the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>to that model and form which they have fancied, diſturb her peace, which we heartily rejoyce to ſee reſtored among you.</hi> To which I will add his Words in his Letter to the Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> A. D. 1572. <hi>I would never have ſent my Son into</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>the only Son by my Wife</hi> Zuinglia, <hi>(whoſe memory is dear to me) except I had throughly perſwaded my ſelf of our conſent and agreement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caſaubon</hi> in his Ephemeris, <hi>A. D. 1610, Nov. 1ſt,</hi> in <hi>Moulin</hi>'s Def. p. 7. hath this Prayer, <hi>Thou, O Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, preſerve the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and give a ſound mind to the Nonconformiſts, who deride the Rites and Ceremonies of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Learned <hi>Bochart</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Durel. Thoſe who refuſe to communicate with the Church of</hi> England, <hi>becauſe of her Ceremonies are Schiſmaticks; find your Liturgy very good, and well ordered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Capellus in Theſ. Salm. de Liturgia. <hi>Of late there aroſe in</hi> England, <hi>a froward, ſcrupulous, and overnice, (not to ſay Superſtitious) Generation of Men, who not only blame, but Caſhire and Aboliſh the Liturgy uſed hitherto in their Church,—for cauſes very trivial and almoſt of no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at all,—the Lord grant that they may come to a better mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Claude</hi> in his Letter publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet. The Diſſenters holding their Aſſemblies apart, ſeparating from the publick Aſſemblies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is real Schiſm, odious to God and Man, of which the Authors and Patrons cannot avoid rendring an account before the Tribunal of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Le Moyne,</hi> in his Letter <hi>A. D.</hi> 1660, publiſhed by <hi>Durell. If ever any made their ungratefulneſs notorious, they are the Engliſh oppoſers of Epiſcopacy.—What good have theſe troublers of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that are ſo contrary to Biſhops done, for well nigh Twenty Years, that they have ruled? Have not</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62742:12"/> 
               <hi>all things grown worſe? Hereſy grown bold?—Did ever Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan work more miſchief than ſince the time that theſe Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Maſters,—for a re-union of all the foreign Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches the King of</hi> England <hi>muſt preſerve the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</hi> And in his Letter publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet.—Whence is it that ſome Engliſh Men have ſo ill an opinion of the Church of England, and divide raſhly from her, as they do? Is not this to divide from all the Ancient Churches, from all the Proteſtant Churches, which have always had a very great reſpect for the purity of that of</hi> England?—<hi>I look upon theſe Men as Diſturbers of the State and Church, and who are doubtleſly animated by a Spirit of Sedition;—Societies compoſed of ſuch Perſons, would be extreamly dangerous, and could not be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered without opening the Gate to diſorder, and advancing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ones own ruine,—to cantonize themſelves and make a Schiſm, to have the liberty to vent ſuch vanities, is very ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Goyon</hi> in his Letter publiſhed by <hi>Durell. Thoſe are in a Dream and dote, who have an Opinion that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is wounded by living under the Engliſh Liturgy; and they wrong us very much, when they quote us to foment a Schiſm ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſcandalous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I have given the judgements of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Men of the Reformed Religion, of <hi>France, Holland</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> and ſhewed what opinion they have of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as by Law eſtabliſhed, and what opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they have of the Diſſenters from it; and whoever ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſiders theſe things, will find no reaſon for us to alter our eſtabliſhment, in order to an union and comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the foreign Reformed Churches. Its hard to meet with any one conſiderable Proteſtant Writer that ſpeaks ill of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> beſides the Diſſenters that live amongſt us, and ſome few that have been preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced by them. And ſhould we compare the Eulogies and Praiſes that theſe Foreign Divines give the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62742:12"/> with the opprobrious Language it generally receives from our own own Diſſenters, we muſt conclude that they and the Foreign Divines are not of the ſame judgment. I will mention only the Divines of the <hi>Savoy</hi> Conference, <hi>p.</hi> 3. where we have their Synodical Judgment in theſe words; <hi>We take the Common-Prayer to be a Defective, Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and inconvenient mode of Worſhip, it would be a Sin to uſe it,</hi> &amp;c. How different is their Language from that of the Foreign Divines?</p>
            <p>But leſt it be objected that theſe are only general Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions I have mentioned, and that notwithſtanding all this, the Foreign Churches would be glad to have theſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations made which have been propoſed; I will next con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider moſt of the things that have been inſiſted on to be changed, and ſee whether the Foreign Reformed Churches will be better pleaſed with them as they now are, or as thoſe that delight in change would have them. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Kalendar</hi> is the firſt thing inſiſted on to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, we will begin with that; and firſt the Reading of Apocryphal Chapters in the Church, and eſpecially the Book of <hi>Tobit,</hi> by which (ſaith one of them,) <hi>we give too much countenance to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and ſupplant Canonical Scripture,</hi> &amp;c. Now to ſee how very little reaſon is for this Objection, let it be obſerved,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That our Church always calls theſe Books Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal, and thereby ſufficiently diſtinguiſheth them from the Canonical, and her ſelf from Popery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Thirty Nine Articles of Religion, ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>That ſhe reads them for example of Life and inſtruction of Manners, but yet doth not apply them to eſtabliſh any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. All our Divines that have written upon this Subject, eſpecially <hi>Reynolds</hi> and <hi>Coſins,</hi> have ſo Learnedly and unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably baffled the Papiſts, that they have never thought good to reply to them.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62742:13"/>4. Our Church hath taken ſo great care in this matter to avoid giving offence, that ſeveral of theſe Books are never Read in the Church at all, as the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> Books of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> Prayer of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and the famous Fifth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Tobit,</hi> about him and his Dog, which hath been left out of our Church from the beginning of King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>1ſt,</hi> almoſt an 100 Years; the other Books that are ordered to be Read in the Church, are never read on Sundays, but only Week-days.</p>
            <p>Now our Church in allowing of them ſometimes to be Read, doth much better agree with the Primitive Church, than ſhe would if they were ſhut quite out; for 'tis certain that they publickly Read them. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> or the Author of the Synopſis calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. not <hi>received into the Canon, but read in the Church,</hi> Ruffinus in Symb. <hi>Alii libri ſunt qui non Canonici ſed Eccleſiaſtici a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joribus appellati ſunt,</hi> Tobit, Judeth, <hi>&amp;c. quae omnia legi qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem in Eccleſia voluerunt, non tamen Profeſſi ad Authoritatem fidei confirmandam.</hi> i. e. <hi>There are Books which are not Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal but Eccleſiaſtical, as</hi> Tobit, Judeth, <hi>&amp;c. all which are read in the Church, but not produced to confirm any Article of Faith.</hi> Which is exactly agreeable to the words of St. <hi>Hierom</hi> in his Preface to his Commentary upon <hi>Proverbs,</hi> and which are quoted and approved of by our Church in the Thirty Nine Articles. <hi>Gregorius Magnus</hi> in Moral. <hi>l. 19. c. 13. Art.</hi> 6, may ſpeak for the ſucceeding Ages, where he calls theſe Books, <hi>though not Canonical, yet publiſhed for the Edification of the Church.</hi> That they were Read in the <hi>African</hi> Churches, appears from one of the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Councils, at which St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> was preſent, 3 <hi>Carthag. Can.</hi> 47. That they have been all along read in the Weſtern Churches, appears from <hi>Iſidore de Eccleſ. Off. Rabanus de inſtit. Cler.</hi> &amp;c. And laſtly, the <hi>Lectionarius</hi> publiſhed by <hi>Pame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> and which goeth under the name of St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> and hath been of great Uſe and Authority in the Weſtern Churches, gives an account of particular days, when particular places of the Apocryphal Books were appointed to be read in the Church. As to the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62742:13"/> the author of the <hi>Synopſis</hi> already mention'd, <hi>Origene</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Affricanus</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the hiſtory of</hi> Suſannah <hi>was read</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in every Church of Chriſt.</hi> And again, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Churches make uſe of the book of Tobit.</hi> And as to their preſent practice, beſides their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> printed at <hi>Venice, A. D.</hi> 1596. which contains their ſeveral leſſons for the whole year, and hath ſeveral taken out of the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> we have the expreſs authority of one that lived amongſt them, Mr. <hi>Rycaut</hi> in his Hiſtory of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, p. 372. <hi>In the</hi> Greek <hi>Church they receive the Apocryphal Books as we do in</hi> England. In the <hi>Ethiopick</hi> Churches they read the Athcpocryphal Books, as appears from <hi>Ludolfus's</hi> Hiſtory of thoſe Churches; and laſtly, by the works of <hi>Hippolytus, Origen,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> St. <hi>Hierome, Theodore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Aſterius, Leo Magnus,</hi> and others, it appears that the Fathers not only wrote Comments upon theſe books, but frequently preach'd upon them, and took their Texts thence; not to mention that <hi>Conradus Pellican, Druſius,</hi> and ſome other Reformed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, have without any offence wrote comments upon them as upon other parts of the Bible.</p>
            <p>If from this general agreement of all the Chriſtian Churches in the World, we conſider in the laſt place the judgment of the Reformed Churches, we ſhall find them alſo agree with us. 1. For the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally uſe them as we do, and <hi>Alſted</hi> in <hi>Theol. Pol. p.</hi> 287. gives this account of them, that they are <hi>ſacri ſecundum quid, &amp; populare quadam ratione, &amp; merito proxime a vere divinis lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum obtinere poſſunt,</hi> i. e. that <hi>they are in a ſenſe ſacred, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the next place to the Canonical Scriptures.</hi> And <hi>Chemnitius</hi> in <hi>examen. poſt. 1. de. ſer. can.</hi> ſpeaking of the Apocryphal Books, ſaith, <hi>A fidelibus in Eccleſiis leguntur,</hi> i. e. <hi>they are read by the Orthodox in the Churches.</hi> And then for the Churches of the Calviniſts, firſt hear <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf in <hi>Pſychopannichia, Melius nos decent ſacrae literae, corpus quod corrumpitur aggravat animam,</hi> i. e. <hi>the holy Writings teach us better, that the corruptible body oppreſſeth the Soul.</hi> And yet thoſe Sacred Writings are the book called the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> from whence that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is taken. <hi>Conradus Pelicanus,</hi> in his preface to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62742:14"/> upon the Apocryphal Books, ſaith of them that they are <hi>Eccleſiaſtici ac Biblici &amp; in Eccleſia Catholica ab Apoſtolorum temporibus fuerint cum reverentia lecti,</hi> i. e. <hi>theſe books are read in the Church, and bound up with our Bibles, and have with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence been read in all Chriſtian Churches from the very time of the Apostles,</hi> and he was a famous Profeſſor at <hi>Zurich. Lud. Capellus in Theſ. Salm.</hi> expreſly approves of the <hi>Declaration of our Church in her 39 Articles, and ſaith that profit may come to the Church by their being read publickly; and ſo they were read in the Primitive times for the instruction of manners. Epiſcopius</hi> Profeſſor at <hi>Leyden,</hi> in <hi>Tom. 2. Part. 2. p. 75. though the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphal Books cannot ſerve to confirm an Article of Faith, yet may profitably be read in 'the Church.</hi> And indeed, of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Churches, we have their ſolemn judgment declared in the Synod of <hi>Dort. Art. 6. We make a difference betwixt the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical and Apocryphal Books, which laſt are the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> and 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of</hi> Eſdras, Tobit, Judeth, <hi>&amp;c. which the Church may read, and take inſtructions in them agreeable to Canonical Scripture:</hi> The Bibles of <hi>Holland, Geneva,</hi> and other reformed Churches, have theſe books prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quere in Deodats, &amp; Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Bibles.</hi>
               </note> and bound up with the Canonical as we have; and in the Preface to the Apocryphal Books, they commend the very ſentences of <hi>Ruffinus</hi> and St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> which declare for the publick reading of them in the Churches. And the like is done by the Publiſhers of the Harmony of the Confeſſions of all the Reformed Churches Printed at <hi>Geneva;</hi> and laſtly, the Reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> in their Book of Diſcipline, <hi>p.</hi> 391. have this rule, <hi>Les livres de la Bible ſoit Canonique ou autres ne ſeront transformez en Comedies ou Tragedies,</hi> i. e. <hi>the books of the Bible, whether Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical or others, ſhall not be uſed in Plays;</hi> in which Words, they firſt call theſe Apocryphal books part of the Bible, and then take care that they be not prophaned. And thus it's evident, that all the Primitive and Purer Ages of the Church, all the <hi>Eaſtern, Weſtern,</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Churches, all the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran</hi> and <hi>Calviniſtical</hi> Churches beyond Sea, do either read theſe books publickly in their Churches, or very expreſly approve of it; nor is there any one inſtance of any Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62742:14"/> Church that ſince the Reformation, read them publickly as we have done, but ſtill continues to do ſo; and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Diſſenters are condemned by all the Churches in the World, in leaving them out of their Bibles, who were the firſt body of Chriſtians, as far as I can find, that ever did ſo.</p>
            <p>To make this the more evident, I ſhall here give a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of the publick large Bibles, of all the Countries I could meet with; in all which, upon examination, I find the Apocryphal added, for the ſame intent as in ours, <hi>viz. For the Example of Life, and the Inſtruction of Manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Catalogue of Bibles Printed with the</hi> Apocrypha.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer's</hi> Preface, <hi>Lond.</hi> 1541.</item>
               <item>By <hi>Coverdale, Lond.</hi> 1550.</item>
               <item>By Command of Q. <hi>Eliz. Lond.</hi> 1578.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Welch, Lond.</hi> 1588</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scotch, Edenburgh.</hi> 1596.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> tranſlated by <hi>Wicliff</hi> a <hi>M. S.</hi> with a Prologue, in which are theſe words, <hi>Holy Church readeth,</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>and</hi> Toby, <hi>and the Books of</hi> Maccabees, <hi>but receiveth not them among Holy Scriptures; ſo the Church readeth the two Books</hi> Eccleſiaſtici <hi>and</hi> Sapience, <hi>to edify the People, not to confirm the Authority of Teaching.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bohemian,</hi> 1613.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Daniſh</hi> at <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> 1550.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>French</hi> at <hi>Geneva,</hi> 1588</item>
               <item>At <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> 1669</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>German,</hi> 1604</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Luther's</hi> Tranſlation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> 1617</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Frankfurt,</hi> 1580</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Armenian</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> 1666</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spaniſh</hi> by Proteſtants, <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> 1602.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hungarian,</hi> by the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Biſhops of <hi>Hungary,</hi> at <hi>Hannover</hi> and <hi>Oppen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim,</hi> 1608</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Muſcovitiſh</hi> at <hi>Oſtrogoth,</hi> 1581</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Italian</hi> by <hi>Deodate,</hi> 1607</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Latin,</hi> by <hi>Caſtalion,</hi> dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th. <hi>Baſ.</hi> 1573</item>
               <item>By <hi>Junius,</hi> dedicated to <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> 1592</item>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62742:15"/>
               <item>By <hi>Robert Stephens, Paris,</hi> 1540</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Critici Sacri 9 Tomis Lond. 1666</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hebrew.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Polyglott. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Lond.</hi> 1567</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Septuagint.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Syrtach.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vulgar <hi>Latin.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And indeed, amongſt all the <hi>Bibles</hi> which I have ſeen, I find them only left out in the <hi>Spaniſh Bible,</hi> examin'd by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors, printed at <hi>Ferara 1553,</hi> and that of <hi>New-En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> in the <hi>Virginian</hi> Tongue, printed at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>New-England</hi> 1663. So that if to comply with our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Diſſenters, we muſt ſtrike out theſe <hi>Apocryphal</hi> books, I know no Bibles we ſhall follow, but that of the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Commiſſioners of <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to conclude this head, I ſhall put down theſe five obſervations:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That no Papiſt ever made uſe of this as an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that our Church own'd theſe Books as Canonical, ſo that there could be no feal ground for this objection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That there neither is, nor ever was any one Chriſtian Church in the whole World that had ſet Leſſons appointed for every day in the year, as we have, but ſome of them were taken out of the <hi>Apocrypha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That no one foreign Church whatſoever did ever declare themſelves offended with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this matter, but as I have ſhewed, generally approve it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That theſe very perſons who complain of our reading Apocryphal Chapters for Leſſons, make no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of having Hymns printed in their Bibles before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms in meeter, and being frequently uſed in the Church inſtead of them. Which is agreeable to the practice of <hi>Holland,</hi> where that Church before Sermon ſings a Hymn, compoſed by one <hi>John Wittenhaven,</hi> as we do any one of our Pſalms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That the great Promoters of this objection do not ſtop here, but urge it to the laying aſide Sermons and Homilies, as not being within the Canon; yea, and the Scripture and Leſſons themſelves, and as we have reaſon to fear laying aſide all publick ſervice whatſoever. <hi>T. C.</hi> in his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62742:15"/> admonition, <hi>p. 221. would have no Homilies read in the Church, becauſe nothing but the voice of God, and holy Scriptures, ſhould ſound in his Church;</hi> and this will deſtroy Sermons and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo. The Author anſwered by Biſhop <hi>Nicolſon</hi> in his Apology, <hi>p.</hi> 184. is <hi>angry with our Church for reading two Leſſons, and would have but one:</hi> And that Leſſon alſo is in danger by the Author of the Letter to the Convocation, <hi>p.</hi> 21. where he propoſeth the <hi>leaving out the firſt Leſſon in the Afternoon upon ſhort days, and in Country Pariſhes to read Prayers without Leſſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that upon the whole, however it ſeems to ſome a ſmall, to others a reaſonable matter, I do not ſay to leave out, for then that ſhould have been done at firſt, but to reject the Apocryphal Leſſons, yet in this we ſhall ſeparate from the Primitive, the Eaſtern, Weſtern and <hi>African</hi> Churches, from moſt of the Reformed Churches; we muſt alter the 39 Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Religion, which have been ſo generally received and applauded, for they declare that the Church doth read them. We muſt alter our Apologies and Canons, for there <hi>(Canon. 30. Juells Apol. p.</hi> 170.) it's declared, that <hi>it was ſo far from the purpoſe of the Church of</hi> England <hi>to forſake and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Churches of</hi> Italy, France, Spain, Germany, <hi>and other Churches, in all things which they hold and practis'd, that, as the Apology of the Church of</hi> England <hi>confeſſeth, it only departed from them in thoſe particular points, wherein they were faln both from themſelves in their ancient integrity, and from the Apoſtolical Churches.</hi> To this agreeth the Apology for Proteſtants, by a <hi>French</hi> Divine, and tranſlated <hi>A. D. 1681. p. 23. As to the reproach caſt upon our firſt Reformers, it is one of the greateſt injuſtices in the world, for nothing can be clearer from their own writings, than that it was never their intent to ſubvert the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Government of the Church, nor to aboliſh thoſe Religious Rites and Holy Ceremonies, which the piety of the primitive Chriſtians had introduced, but only to take away the abuſes of them.</hi> So that in making unneceſſary changes in theſe things, we ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the very foundation and principle of the Reformation. And that this rule is properly applied to the matter in hand, is evident from the declaration of our Church at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62742:16"/> of the Liturgy, where the reading of the Leſſons as is appointed, <hi>is called a godly and decent order of the ancient Fathers—agreeable to the mind and purpoſe of the old Fathers.</hi> Upon all which accouuts it is evident, that we ought not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the taking away the Apocryphal Leſſons, and that the Reformed Churches do not deſire it of us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to the Rules and Tables for finding <hi>Eaſter,</hi> great objections have been raiſed againſt our Church, and ſome Eminent Diſſenters have declared that they could not give their aſſent and conſent to our Liturgy, becauſe theſe were falſe. Now by falſe they do not mean that they are contrary to Scripture, for there are no Rules in the New Teſtament for this purpoſe, and that in the Old, for finding their firſt Months in the Year, by the approaching Harveſt, and Offering their Firſt-fruits on the ſixteenth of the firſt Month, cannot poſſibly agree to us whoſe Harveſt is not ripe till the latter part of the year. But by falſe, they generally mean that they are not agreeable to themſelves, and whereas our rule to find <hi>Eaſter</hi> is to keep it on the firſt <hi>Sunday,</hi> after the firſt full Moon, after the twenty firſt of <hi>March,</hi> by our very Tables as they ſay it appears that we frequently keep it otherwiſe. Now this is a great miſtake, and ſhows the Ignorance of thoſe that object it. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers met at the firſt Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and thoſe before that time alſo did generally agree, that <hi>Eaſter</hi>-day ſhould always be kept on the <hi>Sunday,</hi> the day of Chriſts Reſurecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therein the Chriſtians differed from the Jews, who kept the Paſſover any day of the Week. They alſo agreed to keep it after the Vernal Equinox, and in this they agreed with the Elder Jews, <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> the Author of the Book of <hi>Enoch, Philo, &amp;c,</hi> as it is obſerved by <hi>Anatolius</hi> in <hi>Euſebius.</hi> And laſtly, at or after the full Moon, according as God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the obſervation of the Paſſover in the Book of <hi>Exodus.</hi> Now becauſe theſe were great diſputes about the preciſe day of the Venral Equinox, and Aſtronomers have not yet learned to Calculate a New-Moon exactly, and one quarter of an hour near the diviſion of a Day, may make the New-Moon a day ſooner or later, therefore the Fathers in the <hi>Nicene</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62742:16"/> Council, and other Learned Men ſince, have eſteemed it the beſt way to appoint a fix'd Equinox, and a perpetual rule for the diſcovery of the New-Moons, which if in long Tract of time ſhould vary from the true Equinox, and the true New-Moons; yet ſuch errour would not create that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and diſorder in the Church, which continually aroſe by their ſeveral Calculations, and this was called the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical New-Moon. All Wiſe men conſtantly obſerving that it was not a matter of ſo great moment, whether we kept <hi>Eaſter</hi> a little ſooner or later, ſo that all Churches would agree in the ſame time, and there might be no Schiſm in the body. Now the Equinox was fix'd by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council on the twenty firſt of <hi>March,</hi> and that hath been conſtantly obſerv'd by all Chriſtian Churches of the World, as the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Equinox, till <hi>A. D.</hi> 1582. when it was alter'd by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13th, which was ſince the beginning of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and our rejecting the Papal Supremacy. Then for the diſcovery of the New-Moons for ever, they having obſerv'd that the New-Moons after 19 years returned to the ſame days of the Month, in a <hi>Julian</hi> year, and very near the ſame time of the day, they made a Cycle of New-Moons for 19 years according to the skill of the beſt Calculators of that Age, and order'd that Cycle to be of perpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ual uſe in the Church for the diſcovery of the Paſchal New-moons. Which for its great uſe, and eſtabliſhing peace and union in the Chriſtian Churches, was put down in all their Kalendars in Golden Letters, and thence call'd the Golden number. <hi>Ambroſe Epiſt. 83. Majores noſtri convenientes ad Synodum Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caenam congregatis peritiſſimis calculandi, novemdecem annorum collegere rationem, &amp; quaſi quendam conſtituere circulum, quem Enneadecaterida vocant, &amp;c.</hi> Dionyſ. Exig. Ep. 1. <hi>Venerabiles 318 Pontifices qui Nicaeae convenerent 14mas lunas paſchalis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervantiae per 19 annorum circulum ſtabiles, immoteſque fixerunt, quae cunctis ſaeculis eodem quo reponuntur Exordio ſine varietatis labuntur excurſu, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Church likewiſe hath taken care to print this very Cycle of New-Moons in the firſt Column of her Kalendar, ſee <hi>Iſidor. Orig. p.</hi> 967. by which the Eccleſiaſtical Full-Moon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62742:17"/> is diſcovered. And to make all plain, in our great Church Bibles, this is explained in theſe words; <hi>The Golden number is ſo called, becauſe it was written in the Kalender with letters of Gold, right at the day whereon the Moon changed, and it is the ſpace of 19 years,</hi> &amp;c. And tho' in this ſpace of almoſt 1300 years ſince that Council, this Cycle of New Moons is too late for the true New-Moons in the Heavens by 4 days and ſome hours, yet no Chriſtian Church in the world did go about to diſturb the peace and quiet of the Church in ſuch a trivial matter, till it was about 100 years ſince very Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matically alter'd by Pope <hi>Gregory.</hi> To bring this matter to a Concluſion, let it be obſerved,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That our Kalendar is agreeable to it ſelf, and if we find the New-Moons according to this ancient and authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Cycle, we always keep <hi>Eaſter</hi> the firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> after the firſt Full-Moon, after the Vernal Equinox fix'd upon the 21ſt of <hi>March.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That in following this method we agree with all the Chriſtian Churches in the World, from the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> to <hi>A. D. 1582. i. e.</hi> for the ſpace of near 1200 years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That we now agree with the Greek Church and all the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Chriſtians who keep <hi>Eaſter</hi> at the ſame time as we do. (For the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Armenian</hi> Churches, ſee Mr. <hi>Rycaut,</hi> p. 416: for <hi>Ethiopick</hi> Churches ſee <hi>Ludolfus, &amp;c.)</hi> And withal thoſe Proteſtants whoſe Reformation was eſtabliſhed by the conſent and agreement of the Regal authority before the alteration made by Pope <hi>Gregory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It's an opinion very agreeable to the peace and union of Chriſtian Churches that that which hath been once eſtabliſhed by an Univerſal Council, ought not to be altered by a Provincial Synod, and this matter having been famouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſettled by the firſt general Council, and that alſo as to this particular confirmed by ſeveral others, and by the firſt Council of <hi>Antioch</hi> all ordered to be excommunicated that diſobeyed it, we ought not to make alterations. And I pray let it be obſerved that our Church did by her repreſentatives give conſent to ſome of thoſe very Councils. At the Council of <hi>Arles</hi> in <hi>France, A. D.</hi> 314. were preſent three <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62742:17"/> and the very firſt Canon agreed on there was this, <hi>Ut uno die &amp; tempore Paſcha celebretur,</hi> i. e. <hi>That Eaſter ſhould be every where kept the ſame day.</hi> Which ſeems to have been the very firſt reſolution about this matter in the Council of <hi>Nice. Euſeb. vit. Conſt. l. 3. c.</hi> 18. And <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Letter giving an account of the firſt Council at <hi>Nice,</hi> expreſly gives us the agreement alſo of the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Churches, to the keeping <hi>Eaſter</hi> after that method. <hi>Euſeb. vit. conſt. l. 3. c.</hi> 19. Socrates <hi>Hiſt.</hi> p. 285.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let it be conſidered, before we change, how we ſhall alter, for either we muſt follow the new method of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Decree of Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> and therein we ſhall not only take away our agreement with the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches, but ſhall more than ever be cryed out againſt by the Diſſenters, for complying with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Or elſe we muſt eſtabliſh a particular method of our own, and that would look very ill, and far from promoting the peace and union of Chriſtian Churches, that in a thing ſo very indifferent in its own nature, we ſhould fall from and contradict all the Chriſtian Churches in the World. How much ſuch an alteration would tend to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Faction and Schiſm, I leave all the World to judge.</p>
            <p>I paſs by the ſilly objection of our keeping two <hi>Eaſters</hi> in one year. For if by year we mean the exact revolution of 365 days, according to all rules now uſed in the Chriſtian World, we muſt keep two <hi>Eaſters</hi> in one year, every third year, or thereabouts. Or if we mean that we keep two <hi>Eaſters</hi> betwixt one 25th of <hi>March,</hi> and the next, this may be eaſier mended by beginning our year only at <hi>Jan.</hi> firſt, as is the more uſual way, and ſo there is never two <hi>Eaſters</hi> in one <hi>Almanack.</hi> And if we kept <hi>Easter</hi> according to the true New-Moons, and the true Equinox, the ſame objection would continue, and always muſt ſo long as our beginning of the year is betwixt the Paſchal Terms, whereof the firſt was always fix'd at the Equinox, which now happens before the 25th of <hi>March,</hi> this being the nature of movable Feaſts.</p>
            <p>I may very well paſs by alſo the objecting of the Saints and Biſhops Names continued in our Kalender, which as it's
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62742:18"/> generally uſed in the Lutheran Churches, ſo is evidently done for a Civil, and not any Religious uſe, as hath been long ſince declared in the Preface to <hi>Peces Privatae</hi> publiſhed by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <hi>A. D.</hi> 1573. The words are, <hi>Not that we repute them all for Saints or holy men, but that they may be as notes of ſome certain things, and fixed ſeaſons, the knowledge of which is very beneficial;</hi> of which ſort are <hi>Hilary, Valentine, David,</hi> St. <hi>George, Martin, Swithin, Lammas, Giles, Holyrood, Eviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, All-Souls, Leonard. Cicilia, O Sapientia,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo as far as I can ſee, the only way to continue peace and union amongſt our ſelves, and with other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches, is to continue the Kalender as it is.</p>
            <p>Paſs we next to the grand objection againſt the old verſion of the Pſalms, uſed in the Common-Prayer-Book, and the way propoſed for the amending it, not by taking that of our Bibles, which is not liked, but a more correct one in their hands. So the Author of a Letter from the Country, <hi>p. 6. The Pſalter added to our Liturgy, is not now ſo defenſible, when there is a more correct in our hands—then complains of its mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold variations from the</hi> Hebrew, <hi>and frequently miſtaking the ſenſe—this muſt needs create no little ſcruple in Mens minds, by having inconſiſtent and differing Tranſlations.</hi> Again, p. 13. <hi>in comparing the two Tranſlations of the Pſalms, we find them in ſome things inconſiſtent, and one time the one to deny what the other affirms,</hi> viz. Pſal. 105. 28. And again, the Letter to the Convocation, <hi>p. 15. muſt we be forc'd to read the old Tranſlation of the Pſalms, and impoſe that on the people for true Scripture, which in ſo great a number of places quite differs from it?</hi> Here is in all this complaint not one word of the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pſalms, which are not only different in Words, and Phraſes, from both of them, but in the ſenſe alſo, as being compoſed from a more ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſion than either of them. And ſo the Proteſtant Churches of <hi>France</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to Sing the Pſalms according to <hi>Marrot's</hi> compoſition, full of uncouth words and expreſſions, <hi>Apol.</hi> for <hi>Prot. p.</hi> 76. and read their Bible according to a Verſion made at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reformation. <hi>p.</hi> 82. which looks as if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of theſe Objections were of a Presbyterian Original,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62742:18"/> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> have a great Veneration for <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Sternhold,</hi> and a natural antipathy to the Common-Prayer. However weighty this Argument be to us at home, yet Foreigners are not concern'd in it: And tho <hi>(however we do not do it, moſt certainly the Parliament will)</hi> as ſaith the Author of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Convocation, <hi>p.</hi> 23. It was far otherwiſe in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> time, when the Convocation was very earneſt upon this very deſign of altering the Tranſlation of the Pſalms in the Liturgy, and were by the Parliament ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly diſſwaded from it. <hi>Hammond L'Eſtrange's</hi> Alliance of Divine Offices, <hi>p.</hi> 75. But the beſt is, this confident gueſſer is here miſtaken alſo, and our old Tranſlation hath outlived that Parliament. Not to mention that if we lay aſide this Verſion, and take a new correct one, never yet Printed, into our Liturgy, the objection remains as at firſt, and here may be as much difference betwixt the Pſalms in the Common-Prayer, of a new more correct Edition, and that in our Bibles, as is now. Nor was it ever propoſed, or ſo much as hinted in the Commiſſion to the Convocation, to have a new Tranſlation of the Bible. As to the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion uſed in the Liturgy, it is not made from the Verſion of the Septuagint, nor from the Vulgar Latin, as is evident to any one that will compare them. And King <hi>James's</hi> Tranſlators of the Bible, declare of the <hi>meanest of our</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Tranſlations of the Bible, that they were the Word of God.</hi> And tho in ſome places, it ſeems rather to agree with the Septuagint, yet it ſeems done chiefly in ſuch places, where we have great reaſon to believe, that the Septuagint is more correct, and more agreeable, to the Original <hi>Hebrew.</hi> So <hi>Pſalm</hi> 14. 5, 6, 7. are not in our preſent <hi>Hebrew</hi> Bibles, but yet are quoted thence by St. <hi>Paul, Rom. 3. 10, 11, 12, 13, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 4. our Common-Prayer reads it—<hi>and clear when thou art judged;</hi> agreeable to St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 3. 4. but the Verſion uſed in our Bibles is different from both: <hi>Clear when thou judgeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we would but take the pains to compare both Tranſlations of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> with the common Verſion of the New Teſtament, it will be eaſie to find many places where
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62742:19"/> our old Tranſlation is more agreeable to the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; of which take theſe few inſtances:</p>
            <p>Mat. 1. 43. <hi>He truſted in God, let him deliver him now if he will have him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 8. in the Liturgy. <hi>He trusted in God, that he would deliver him, let him deliver him if he will have him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 8. in the Bible. <hi>He truſted on the Lord that he would deliver him, let him deliver him, ſeeing he delighted in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rom. 10. 18. <hi>Their ſound went into all the earth, and their words unto the ends of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 4. in the Liturgy. <hi>Their ſound is gone out into all lands, and their words into the ends of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 4. in the Bible. <hi>Their line is gone out through all the earth, and their words to the end of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rom. 11. 10. <hi>And bow down their back alway.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. 24. in the Liturgy. <hi>And ever bow down their backs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. 23. in the Bible. <hi>And make their loyns continually to ſhake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Pet. 3. 11. <hi>Let him eſchew evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 14. in the Liturgy. <hi>Eſchew evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 14. in the Bible. <hi>Depart from Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that it was no doubt, the wiſdom of thoſe that compiled this Verſion in our Liturgy, to conſider the Authentick Tranſlation made by the Holy Ghoſt in the New Teſtament; and if we ſhould admit the ſame Verſion of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> into the Liturgy, which is in the Bible, theſe men of ſcruples might be at as great a loſs to reconcile the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and the ſecond Leſſon, read preſently after them, as they now are to reconcile the two Verſions of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and at as great a loſs to reconcile both with the Singing <hi>Pſalms,</hi> which were certainly compoſed by as old, or older Verſion, than that in the Common-Prayer-Book.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62742:19"/>
            <p>As to that one place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 28. which hath been often urged by the Presbyterians, from the very days of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> and as often anſwered, ſo that I cannot but admire at the ignorance of the diligent <hi>Will. Prynne</hi> in this matter, who in his Pacifick Examination of the Common-Prayer, <hi>p.</hi> 6. where having propoſed this objection againſt the Tranſlation of <hi>Pſalm</hi> 105. 28. tells us, that it was occaſioned by the Printers omiſſion of one ſyllable, to wit, <hi>Obedient</hi> for <hi>Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient,</hi> not the Tranſlators. But to paſs this by, <hi>Hooker</hi> and <hi>Fuller,</hi> in <hi>Miſcel.</hi> ſhew that the Tranſlation in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy beſt agreeth with the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and their judgment is comfirm'd by the <hi>Septuagint, Syriack, Arabick,</hi> and <hi>Ethiopick</hi> Verſions. In the old <hi>Latin</hi> Verſions it was read both ways, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves, <hi>Tom. 8. enarrat.</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> and yet it made no diſturbance in the Church, in that or the following ages. Not to mention that both Verſions are very good ſenſe, and not at all contradictory, in the Liturgy, <hi>they were not obedient,</hi> refers to the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> mention'd <hi>v.</hi> 27. In the Bible, <hi>they rebelled not,</hi> refers to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> v. 26. and even ſo our old Verſion is to be preferr'd, it being more natural for a Verb to refer to the laſt verſe, than the laſt but one; but both are very good ſenſe, and as properly retain'd in our Church, as the different readings were by the <hi>Jews</hi> preſerved in their Bibles. And whoever ſhall give himſelf the trouble to compare the Verſions of the Bible, ſhall have far greater objections than this, <hi>Deut. 21 12. She ſhall pare her nails;</hi> in the Margent of our Bibles, <hi>She ſhall let them grow. Gal.</hi> 2. 3. in the <hi>Greek,</hi> Titus <hi>was not circumciſed.</hi> In many <hi>Latin</hi> copies, <hi>Titus was circumciſed.</hi> And again, <hi>v.</hi> 5. in the <hi>Greek, To whom we have not yielded,</hi> in the <hi>Latin, To whom we have yielded;</hi> and this latter was uſed by <hi>Ireneus, l. 3. c. 13.</hi> a <hi>Greek</hi> Father. By <hi>Tertullian, l. 5.</hi> in <hi>Marcion. p. 463.</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe in locum, &amp;c.</hi> and many of the Fathers, as St. <hi>Hierom, Primaſius, Sedulius, Haymo,</hi> &amp;c. freely take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of both readings.</p>
            <p>I might inſtance alſo in <hi>1 Cor. 15. 51.</hi> where ſome read, <hi>We ſhall all ſleep;</hi> of which St. <hi>Hierom</hi> hath a large diſcourſe. Alſo in <hi>Mat. 2. 6.</hi> compared with <hi>Micab 5. 2.</hi> and many
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62742:20"/> other places; not to mention what thoſe very Tranſlators of the Bible, whoſe Verſion is contended for, declared, <hi>That they in many places ſet diverſity of ſenſes in the Margin, for that to determine of ſuch things as the Spirit of God hath left (in the judgment of Judicious) queſtionable, can be no leſs than preſumption:</hi> As St. <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith, <hi>That variety of Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is profitable for finding out the ſenſe of the Scriptures, ſo diverſity of ſenſe in the Margin, where the Text is not ſo clear, muſt needs do good; yea, is neceſſary as we are perſwaded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if any Learned Perſon hath taken pains to make a more correct Verſion than either of theſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church now uſeth, I hope he will not envy the Church the benefit of his labours, but will make it publick, as <hi>Rob. Gell.</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an Eſſay towards the amendment of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Bible, <hi>Lond. 1659.</hi> But I can by no means think it proper to have it propoſed to the Convocation, who upon ſome ſhort examination of it, ſhould Authorize it. When the Clergy are called to the Convocation, they are moſt of them remote from their Boods, and in <hi>London</hi> want leiſure to examine the many difficulties that will ariſe. St. <hi>Hierom</hi> made a more exact Tranſlation of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> than that the <hi>Latin</hi> Church before uſed; he made it publick, and propoſed it to the care and ſtudy of Learned Men to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it, and when an Univerſal Approbation had for ſome Ages given it Authority, it was at laſt received into the Church, inſtead of the other, but not till ſome hundreds of years after the time of St. <hi>Hierom.</hi> And when <hi>Gregory the Great,</hi> about the year 600, compoſed Hymns for the uſe of the Church, it was out of the old Verſion of the <hi>Pſalms.</hi> Nor can it ſeem ſtrange that the ſame Church ſhould uſe two different Verſions of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> for this was done in all the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches, in the time of <hi>Gregory the Great,</hi> who in his Epiſtle Dedicatory, in the beginning of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon <hi>Job,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sedes Apostolica utraque utitur; the</hi> Roman <hi>Church uſeth both Editions. Leander,</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> about the ſame age, wrote a comment upon both Verſions; and Card. <hi>Bona</hi> tells us, that the old Verſion was in frequent uſe till the time of <hi>Pius</hi> V. is ſtill uſed in the Church of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62742:20"/> 
               <hi>Vatiean,</hi> and continued in their Breviaries. When only a Catechiſm was compoſed, not by a ſingle perſon, but a whole Aſſembly of Divines, at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> it was Printed and ſent about, and publick intimation made to the Aſſembly in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that whoever had any objections, might put them in. And when a great many Learned Men were called together, by King <hi>James</hi> l. to correct and review the Tranſlation of the Bible, they were no leſs than three years about it, as they themſelves tell us in their Preface: So that I heartily deſire that Reverend perſon would publiſh his new Verſion, and when time and an univerſal approbation hath given it authority, it may be received into the uſe of the Church, not in the Common-prayer-book only, but Bible alſo. And this hath been done by ſeveral who have made excellent compoſures of the Singing Pſalms, and far better than thoſe we now uſe, and yet the prudence of our Church hath not yet thought fit to give any one of them the ſtamp and ſeal of authority; for this reaſon chiefly, becauſe the Church hath been long uſed to theſe, ſhe hath and can ſing many of them by heart. which as it's the beſt reaſon for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the old Singing <hi>Pſalms,</hi> ſo is much more a reaſon for the continuance of that Verſion in our Liturgy, which is alſo ſung in our Cathedrals and Colleges, and is much better than the other. <hi>Pſalterio Hieronymi ex Hebraicis p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>propagato Eccleſia Romana locum non conceſſit, quia veteri certis conſtricto numeris modulando aſſuetae Christianorum aures, univerſe<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeo Eccleſiae alterius novitatem ferre nunquam potuerunt.</hi> Huetius de interpret. p. 109. Not to mention that in the year 1660, there was far greater reaſon to take the new Tranſlation, which only had been in uſe for 12 years together, into the Liturgy, than to do it now; the old Edition hath been in conſtant uſe for thirty years together, and yet that wiſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation refuſed to do it then.</p>
            <p>The Tranſlation of the Bible, made in the time of King <hi>James</hi> I. was upon the importunate complaints of the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, that they could not ſubſcribe to the Common Prayer-Book, ſince it maintain'd the Bible as it was there Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which was, as they ſaid, a moſt corrupted Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62742:21"/> and yet they were ſome of the firſt that quarrelled at it, as ſoon as it was made, and few or none conform'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account; and the Papiſts preſently clamour'd againſt us for altering our Tranſlation ſo oſt. And the very Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators, after they had examin'd all the old, and made a new Tranſlation, declared, That there was no need of a new Tranſlation, nor of a bad one, to make a good one, but only to make a good one better.</p>
            <p>Next let us conſider the project of leaving out the <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Creed, occaſioned by 4 <hi>four queſtions propoſed againſt it, whereof the laſt is from the Council of</hi> Epheſus, <hi>againſt all addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being made to the Creed, and ſo ſtrikes at the whole Creed, as well as the condemning Sentences.</hi> Letter from the Country, <hi>p.</hi> 14, 15. <hi>Muſt we always pronounce all damn'd, that do not believe every tittle of</hi> Athanaſius'<hi>s Creed,</hi> Letter to the Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>p.</hi> 15. And both theſe give ample incouragement to that Heretical and virulent Book, which at that very time was publiſh'd againſt that Creed, and no leſs againſt the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelf; the Book ſold openly, many of them were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven about, and magnified by the party, without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul of that ſort of men of Latitudinarian principles, till at length it received a juſt cenſure from the honeſt Clergy of the lower Houſe of Convocation; tho at that very time, to the admiration and ſcandal of all ſober men, that very cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was there alſo by great and leading men oppoſed. It's objected by the Author of the Letter from the Country, <hi>p.</hi> 14. he <hi>finds a great diſpute between the</hi> Greek <hi>and</hi> Latin <hi>Church, about the proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt from the Son, now the firſt queſtion is, whither of theſe two Churches be in the right?</hi> Now the proſeſſion of the Holy Ghoſt from the Son is in the <hi>Nice</hi> Creed alſo, received in our Liturgy, and confirm'd by the 39 Articles of our Religion, and Art. 5. expreſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>that the Holy Ghoſt proceedeth from the Father and the Son,</hi> and ſo here is an Article of Faith call'd into queſtion. Not to mention the exact Harmony and Union of all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches of the World in this point. I except only <hi>Arrians, Socinians,</hi> and ſuch other Hereticks who ought not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62742:21"/> to be call'd Proteſtants. And therefore the leaving out of the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed upon ſuch a reaſon muſt needs give great offence to all the Proteſtant Churches in the World. More particularly the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed is at this day approved of and Authoriz'd, by the Confeſſion of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> firſt Publiſhed <hi>A. D. 1561. We receive the three Creeds, Apoſtles,</hi> Nicene <hi>and</hi> Athanaſian <hi>Creed, becauſe they are agreeable to the word of God.</hi> By the Belgick Confeſſion of the Synod of <hi>Dort.</hi> Art. 9. <hi>we willingly receive the three Creeds, the Apostles,</hi> Nicene, <hi>and</hi> Athanaſian <hi>Creeds.</hi> By the Confeſſion of the of the Churches of <hi>Saxony,</hi> Art. 1. <hi>we have always conſtantly embraced the three Creeds, and their natural ſenſe, and by Gods help we will always imbrace them.</hi> By the Confeſſion of <hi>Wirtenberg,</hi> Art 1. <hi>we believe one God and three Perſons, as they are explained in the three Creeds, the Apoſtles,</hi> Nicene <hi>and</hi> Athanaſius'<hi>s.</hi> By the Confeſſion of the <hi>Palatine</hi> Churches, Art. 1. <hi>we believe all things contained in the Holy Scriptures, as they are explain'd in the Apoſtles Creed,</hi> Nicene <hi>and</hi> Athanaſius'<hi>s.</hi> By the Confeſſion of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Churches, Art. 3. <hi>particularly we receive the</hi> Nicene <hi>and</hi> Athanaſian <hi>Creeds.</hi> By the Confeſſion of the Churches of <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Lithuania,</hi> who <hi>A. D.</hi> 1645. expreſly received the <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creeds. The <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Churches receive and uſe theſe three Creeds, <hi>after the Pſalms for the day, the Prieſt readeth the Ten Commandments, and</hi> Athanaſius'<hi>s Creed out of the Service Book.</hi> Pagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Chriſtianogr. p. 81. The very Directory drawn up by the Presbyterians at the <hi>Savoy A. D.</hi> 1661. p. 26. orders the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed to be read in the Church, and laſtly when ſome <hi>Arrians</hi> would have had <hi>Beza</hi> left it out at <hi>Geneva,</hi> he returned this anſwer. Epiſt. 56. <hi>certe in tuam gratiam non mutabitur in Eccleſia Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolum Athanaſij, nec Nicenum cum nemo adhuc inventus eſt qui ſe opponeret quem Deus borrendo judicio non per diderit.</hi> i. e. <hi>certainly for your ſake the Church will not change the</hi> Athanaſian <hi>Creed or the</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene, <hi>ſince no one ever yet oppoſed them, whom God did not destroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let all the World conſider what a ſtrange way here is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the Union of all Proteſtant Churches to the Church of <hi>England, viz.</hi> by laying aſide, or leaving indifferent the uſe of this Creed, which all the Proteſtant Churches in the World, even thoſe of <hi>Geneva, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> do in their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Confeſſions of Faith and Devotions ſo heartily retain and magnifie.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62742:22"/>
            <p>Proceed we next to Baptiſm, and againſt this Office two things are objected, 1. The uſe of the Croſs, 2. Godfathers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Againſt the Croſs, it's propoſed by the Letter from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, p. 8. <hi>to leave the caſe wholly indifferent, to uſe or not uſe the Croſs.</hi> p 9 <hi>If the Miniſter ſcruples the uſe of it, let another perform that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; if any of the Layety let the Miniſter baptize without it.</hi> And the Letter to the Convocation, p. 9. <hi>the Croſs in Baptiſm is become not only uſeleſs, but alſo miſchievous,—occaſions diſſentions and ſchiſms, is an enſign of War to make us fight againſt each other, a Croſs of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereon to crucifie the Lord of Life in his body the Church and rent its bowels aſunder by thoſe lamentable diviſions which it cauſeth amongſt us,—the Church of</hi> England <hi>cannot be guiltleſs if ſhe do not ſomething herein, &amp;c.</hi> It's a ſad thing that the Croſs of Chriſt ſhould produce all this difference amongſt Chriſtians. Well then, let us take away the uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm, and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is likely to be a greater Union amongſt the Chriſtians. Ask all Churches of the World f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om Chriſts time to the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reformation, and they generally all of them uſed the Croſs in Baptiſm for 1500 years, and its ſtrange that all the Chriſtian Churches, for ſo many years ſhould be guilty of ſo dangerous an evil, as the ſign of the Croſs in Baptiſm, nor do I know of any one Church in the World that condemned, or ſo much as ſhewed their diſlike of it for 1500 years. And for the preſent age, it's ſtill retain'd in all the Churches of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, in all the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches, <hi>(Rycant.</hi> p. 168.) in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the <hi>Jacobites, Brerewoods</hi> Enq. <hi>p.</hi> 153.) in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of <hi>AEgypt. Pagitt</hi>'s Chiſtianogr. <hi>p.</hi> 104. in the <hi>Abiſſine,</hi> or <hi>AEthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opian</hi> Churches, <hi>Ludolfi Hiſt. AEthiop. l. 3. c. 6.</hi> in the Churches of the <hi>Muſcovites (Joh. Faber. de relig. Muſcov.)</hi> in the Proteſtant Churches, of the <hi>Ausburg</hi> confeſſion, the Sign of the Croſs is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally uſed in Baptiſm; and for the other Reformed Churches, not one hath declared themſelves offended with us for uſing it, but ſeveral eminent amongſt them have declared for it. <hi>Bucer</hi> declared it an ancient and innocent Rite, and that it might be decently and profitably uſed. The Learned <hi>Caſaubon,</hi> in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Baronius, Exerc. 13. Sect. 33.</hi> commends our holy and prudent Biſhops, who have retain'd this uſe of the Croſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> declared it lawful to profeſs our ſelves Chriſtians by the Sign of the Croſs. <hi>Beza</hi> himſelf ſpeaks favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably of it, in his book <hi>adverſus Baldvinum.</hi> And <hi>Goulartius</hi> of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62742:22"/> 
               <hi>Geneva,</hi> declares it to be a ceremony indifferent. Apology for Proteſtants by a <hi>French</hi> Divine, <hi>p. 87. Touching the Sign of the Croſs, which the Church of</hi> England <hi>retains, to understand it as they do, as a viſible mark that the Infant Baptiz'd is enroll'd as Christs Souldier, ſhould not be aſhamed to confeſs the Faith of Chriſt Crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and fight under his Banner—I ſee no ground at all of exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Ceremony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>William Durel,</hi> in his Sermon on <hi>1 Cor.</hi> 11. 16. had amongſt other things, given the Reformed of <hi>France</hi> an account of our uſing the Sign of the Croſs; he by ſeveral Letters from <hi>De L' Angle Bochart, Daille,</hi> and other eminent Divines of the <hi>French</hi> Church, received its due praiſe and approbation. And now Gods Providence hath ſettled ſo many thouſands of them amongſt us, they readily and willingly make uſe of it, and approve it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> For Godfathers: I find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem not only required in all the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches, but more particularly, <hi>Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glus</hi> in his Book <hi>de Bapt.</hi> is much for the uſe of them, and ſaith, that the clamours raiſed againſt them, were only by the <hi>Anabaptists.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calvin,</hi> in the form of Baptiſm, compoſed for <hi>Geneva,</hi> and which is ſtill uſed there, requires Godfathers at Baptiſm, and they promiſe for the Childs Chriſtian Education, as in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And in an Epiſtle to <hi>Farell,</hi> he hath theſe words, <hi>We require of the Godfathers, that they promiſe to ſee the Children when grown up, instructed in the Faith they are Baptized in. If there be no Godfathers, it's certain the Baptiſm is prophaned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beza,</hi> in his Epiſtles, frequently declares for the uſe and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of them, and particularly in <hi>Ep.</hi> 24. reckons them <hi>among the Constitutions of the Church that bind the Conſcience.</hi> And <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 8. to the Biſhop of <hi>London, That Infants be Baptized in the publick Congregation, with a ſet form of Prayer, that there be Godfathers to engage fortheir Chriſtian Education,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>theſe are plain and honest Rites, ſuch as give no occaſion to Superſtition, and who is there that dare condemn them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Laws of the Church of <hi>Geneva</hi> Sect. 38. <hi>The name of the Infant and Godfather muſt be Registred by the Minister.</hi> (This was heretofore enjojned by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in his Dioceſs; and I have ſeen ſome Regiſters in that Dioceſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appears that injunction was obſerved for ſome time,) <hi>Sect. 39. None are to be Godfathers but the faithful, and thoſe of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> Sect. 40. <hi>they that are ſuſpended from the Lords Supper must not be Godfathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62742:23"/>
            <p>In the Diſcipline of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France, chap. 11. Sect. 7. Tho we have no expreſs commandment of the Lord for Godfathers and Godmothers in Baptiſm, yet becauſe the cuſtom is ancient, and introduced for a good end, thoſe that will not follow ſo good an example, but preſent their Infants themſeves, ſhould be earneſtly exhorted not to be contentious, but to behave themſelves according to this ancient cuſtom, which is good and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</hi> Sect. <hi>12th.</hi> The <hi>Miniſter ſhall diligently admoniſh the Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Godmothers, to conſider the promiſes they have made at the celebration of Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and to this agreeth the Synod of St.</hi> Foy, <hi>A. D. 1578. at</hi> Samues 1596. <hi>at</hi> Montpellier 1598. <hi>which laſt ſaith that Godfathers are obliged not only to inſtruct the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Piety, but alſo in caſe of neceſſity to provide for their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. Sect. 18th, the names of the Godfathers and Godmothers of the Infant ſhall be registred.</hi> Which laſt thing of Regiſtring them as it's generally practis'd by the reformed Churches abroad, ſo is very agreeable to the practice of the Primitive Church, and particularly taken notice of by <hi>Pſeudo Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite.</hi> To all which I beg leave to add the obſervation of Monſieur <hi>Larroque</hi> an eminent Miniſter of the <hi>French</hi> reformed Church in his Book entituled, <hi>Conformite de la Diſcipline Eccleſiaſtique des Proteſtants de France avec celle des anciens Chietiens. A. D.</hi> 1678 and p. 208. he thus writes. <hi>L'uſage des parriens,</hi> &amp;c. i. e. <hi>the uſe of Godfathers and Godmothers to preſent Children in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is very ancient,</hi> Tertullian <hi>makes mention of them in his book of Baptiſm.</hi> chap. 18. <hi>St.</hi> Auſtin <hi>in his 23d Epiſtle, the pretended De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the Areopagite who tells us that they are of Apoſtolick Inſtitution.</hi> Gregory <hi>the 1ſt. in his book of the Sacraments.</hi> Caeſarius <hi>of</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, <hi>in his 12th Homily, the SixthCanon of the Council of</hi> Mets. <hi>A. D.</hi> 888. and indeed the ſubject of that whole Book is to juſtify their Diſcipline from the antiquity of it, and agreement with the primitive Church. I therfore mention this becauſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of this nature are ſo very much ſlighted by our own Diſſenters. This author in the Title page of his book prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this ſentence from the Laws of <hi>Theodoſius, Statuimus obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vari quod priſca Apoſtolica Diſciplina &amp; Canones veteres eloquuntur</hi> i. e. <hi>we command that thoſe things be obſerved which the Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church and old Canons declare for and appoint.</hi> Which I think is more fully explain'd by St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Epiſt. 118. <hi>ad Caſulan. In iis rebus de quibus nihil ſtatuit ſcriptura, mos populi Dei, &amp; inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62742:23"/> majorum pro lege Dei tenenda ſunt;</hi> i. e. <hi>in ſuch things as the Scripture hath not determined, the cuſtom of the Chriſtian Church, and the conſtitutions of our Anceſtors ſhould be obſerved as the Law of God.</hi> To return. Godfathers are alſo uſed in the <hi>Dutch, Rohemian,</hi> and all the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches; the profeſſors of <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yden</hi> in their <hi>Synopſis pur. Theol.</hi> p. 616. declare that <hi>though there is not an abſolute neceſſity of witneſſes in Baptiſm yet the very nature of the thing, and the cuſtom of all the Primitive Church ſhew it to be profit able, and is probably deduced from the practiſe of the</hi> Jews, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 8. 2. Upon which place <hi>Junius</hi> in his Comment is very expreſs, <hi>hinc ritus noster adhibendi teſtes in Baptiſmo,</hi> i. e. <hi>hence came our cuſtom of uſing Godfathers in Baptiſm.</hi> For the uſe of Godfathers in the Church of the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> ſee <hi>Joh: Faber de relig. Muſcov.</hi> For the uſe of them in the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Churches, ſee <hi>Ludolfus.</hi> And now let even our adverſaries be judges whether the laying aſide the uſe of Godfathers, or which amounts to the ſame thing, leaving it as a matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to the Parents diſcretion and choice whether he will have any or not, be not a very unlikely method for us to make uſe of in this Kingdom in order to procure the peace and union of all the Reformed Churches, who no doubt would be highly diſpleas'd and offended with us ſhould we do it.</p>
            <p>Kneeling at the Sacrament hath been often objected againſt by the Diſſenters, and the Letter to the Convocation, <hi>p. 12. would have us be ſo indulgent as to give them the Sacrameut in their own way, and not debar them of it for the ſake of a poſture, to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will be a Sin.</hi> The other Letter, <hi>p. 8. would have it wholly indifferent to kneel, ſtand, or ſit in the Lords Supper.</hi> p. 9. The <hi>Perſon that ſcruples kneeling may have it delivered him in another poſture in his Pew,</hi> &amp;c. And yet if all this was done we ſhould not ſatisfy the Presbyterians who declared at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> p. 61. That <hi>Kneeling at the Lords Table is diſorderly.</hi> And in the Directory. <hi>p. 34. The Communion Table is order'd to be ſo placed that the Communicants may orderly ſit about it.</hi> Now let us go to the Foreign Proteſtant Churches and adviſe with them in this matter, let us go into <hi>Denmark, Norway, Sweden, Germany,</hi> and adviſe with them and all others ſtrictly called Proteſtants, and they all receive the Sacrament Kneeling. The
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62742:24"/> confeſſion of the Faith of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Churches. <hi>Art. 13. Le the miniſters diſtribute the Sacrameut to the Communicants upon their Knees.</hi> And as to their practice, it is to be ſeen in <hi>Comenius ratio Diſciplinae,</hi> &amp;c. Let <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> ſpeak for <hi>Zurick</hi> and the <hi>Swiſſe. Hiſt Sacr l. 5. c. 8. The Sacrament ought to be received devoutly with bending Knees.</hi> At <hi>Geneva,</hi> and in the <hi>French</hi> Churches, they refuſe to adminiſter the Sacrament to any one that ſits, and now they are ſo many of them in <hi>England,</hi> they all receive kneeling, which is agreeable to the Apology for the Reformed Churches written by Monſſeur <hi>Dallee,</hi> chap. 12. p. 56. <hi>Thanks be to God we are not ſo ill taught as to ſcruple the receiving the Sacrament on our Knees: Our Brethren of</hi> England <hi>never receive it otherwiſe, and when we communicate with them we readily conform to their order.</hi> Alſo Apology for Proteſtants written by a <hi>French</hi> Proteſtant. <hi>p. 88. We muſt undoubtedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it of great neceſſity, that the Communion ſhould be received Kneeling, as in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and in</hi> Germany.—<hi>And our Reformers have ſtill been of this opinion, and he quotes</hi> Beza, Calvin, Bucer, <hi>and</hi> Peter Martyr <hi>for it.</hi> And the <hi>Genevians</hi> in their Annotations upon the Harmony of Confeſſions are well contented that every Church ſhould uſe their Liberty in theſe points following, <hi>viz.</hi> Kneeling at the Communion, Organs, and Ember-days, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See <hi>Bancrofts</hi> Survey. <hi>p.</hi> 358. 359.</p>
            <p>The firſt Perſon that introduced ſitting at the Sacrament in <hi>England</hi> was <hi>John a Laſco</hi> an <hi>Arrian,</hi> and he was the chief Perſon that diſturb'd the Churches of <hi>Poland</hi> with this ſloven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not to ſay Impious opinion, as appears from <hi>Wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerſicus's</hi> Hiſtory of the <hi>Sclavonick</hi> Churches, <hi>p.</hi> 129. till at laſt in a great Synod at <hi>Petricovia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> A. D. 1578. It was agreed, That <hi>becauſe ſitting at the Lord's Table is a Rite different from all the Reformed Churches in</hi> Europe, <hi>and they amongſt us were the first Authors of it, who rafhly changing every thing in the Church fell away from us to</hi> Arrianiſm, <hi>therefore let us leave this cuſtom to them, who irreverently treat Chriſt and his Myſteries, I ſay let us leave this cuſtom as neither agreeing to Decency nor Religion, and to many honeſt Perſons extreamly Scandalous.</hi> And again in another Synod at <hi>Wlodiſlavia,</hi> Anno Dom. 1583. <hi>Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the Lord's Table is forbidden in all the Churches of</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Lithuania, <hi>&amp;c. As not being uſed by thoſe of the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62742:24"/> Religion, and being peculiar to the</hi> Arrians. And that we have reaſon to have the ſame fear in <hi>England,</hi> appears from the many <hi>Arrians</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> amongſt us, and more fully by the open Declarations of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans againſt Kneeling at the Sacrament, <hi>They would not at the Communion ſignify their inferiority to Chriſt, nor abaſe themſelves, but think themſelves equals.</hi> Aſſembly at <hi>Perth,</hi> p. 38.</p>
            <p>It's true, that the cuſtom of Kneeling hath been abuſed, in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> to an Idolatrous Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacrament, and ſo hath ſitting and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo. The Prieſt that ſaith Maſs, receiveth the Sacrament ſtanding, and yet adores it. At <hi>Rome</hi> the Popes Deacon receives ſtanding, and the Pope himſelf receives it ſitting. <hi>Card. Bona de rebus Liturg.</hi> p. 490. And <hi>Eſpencaeus de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Adorat. Euch.</hi> l. 2. c. 16. declares that <hi>the Sacrament may be adored, ſitting, ſtanding, lying or kneeling.</hi> The care that was taken in the Churches of <hi>Poland,</hi> was, that there ſhould be an Authentick Declaration, that no adoration of the Elements was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by thoſe that received kneeling, <hi>Harm. confeſſ. p. 237.</hi> So the Church of <hi>England,</hi> took care in the ſecond Edition of the Liturgy, in the Reign of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Sixth, to inſert a Rubrick, declaring, That no Adoration of the Elements, or Sacrament, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by kneeling, and though when the Doctrine of our Church againſt Tranſubſtantiation and Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was ſufficiently known, it was left out in the Reigns of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, yet upon the particular Requeſt of the Presbyterians at the <hi>Savoy, p.</hi> 94. it was again inſerted, with a deſign to give them ſatisfaction, and yet they are after all, as forward to object adoration to us, as if there had been no ſuch Declaration made.</p>
            <p>From all which it's evident, that ſitting is a poſture very oſſenſive and ſcandalous to many other Proteſtant Churches, as well as ours; that kneeling is moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally uſed, and therefore leaving all poſtures indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, as is now propoſed, by ſome of our own Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and was formerly deſired by the Presbyterians
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62742:25"/> at the <hi>Savoy, p.</hi> 56. is a likely way to increaſe the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>T. F.</hi> and the oppoſers of the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, but is never likely to work an union amongſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches. Letter relating to the Convocation, <hi>p. 12. This must be undeniably allowed, that antiquity never uſed Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Sacrament, it having been the conſtant practiſe of all the Churches in the World to communicate ſtanding.</hi> If you ask how this appears, they have nothing to ſay but that the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, in memory of Chriſts Reſurrection, for ſome Ages after it, ſtood at their Prayers on <hi>Sunday,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Easter</hi> and <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi> by which they ſuppoſe that the Sacrament was received in the ſame poſture as they ſaid their Prayers: Their Prayers at other times, were upon their Knees, as indeed this very Order ſuppoſeth, <hi>Tertull. ad Scap. Quando non geniculationibus noſtris ſiccitates depulſae?</hi> i. e. When <hi>did not our ſolemn Prayers, upon our Knees, bring down Rain?</hi> Origen. in Num. c. 4. Hom. 5. <hi>Nam quod flectimus orantes,</hi> &amp;c. where he relates the cuſtom of the Church to pray Kneeling. And in his Book <hi>de Orat. p.</hi> 157. he ſaith that <hi>they generally kneel'd at Prayers, except in caſe of Sickneſs.</hi> Now the Primitive Chriſtians received the Sacrament on other days than <hi>Sunday,</hi> or that ſpace betwixt <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> and that they received it daily, is evident from St. <hi>Cyprian, Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> and many other Fathers; and by conſequence, if they received the Sacrament in a poſture of Prayer, they received it <hi>Kneeling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that there might be a through Reformation, and no part of the Liturgy left entire, ſome have had the confidence to except againſt the Collects themſelves, as too ſhort, and not ſo pertinent: I ſhall only remind ſuch, of what the Devout and Judicious Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> ſaid of them, <hi>viz. That the Collects were the moſt paſſionate, proper, and moſt elegant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions that any language ever afforded; and that there was in them ſuch Piety, and that ſo interwoven with Inſtructions, that they taught us to know the Power, the Wiſdom, the Majeſty and Mercy of God, and much of our duty both to him and our Neighbour.</hi> And if ſome late Collects are intended as a Specimen, by which the old are to be mended, I believe few will rejoice in the change.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:62742:25"/>
            <p>Excommunication for contempt is complain'd of in both the Letters to the Convocation <hi>as a matter highly ſcandalous, and that we thruſt out of the Church the beſt of our People for ſome penny or two penny Cauſe in our Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</hi> Now this Objection is propoſed more peeviſhly than ever it was done by the Diſſenters. After <hi>T. C.</hi> in his Admonition, <hi>p.</hi> 175. the Puritans Petition to Kings <hi>James</hi> I. <hi>A. D. 1603. That Men be Excommunicated for Trifles, and Twelve-penny Matters.</hi> So that from their Objection of Twelve-penny Matters; this Author hath ſtretch'd it to Peny and Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peny Matters. But let us apply our Selves to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Divines of the Foreign Churches, and ſee what they ſay to it. The Dutch Divines in <hi>Sunopſ. Pur. Theol. p.</hi> 710. ſay, <hi>That the Penalty of Excommunication is chiefly incurr'd for neglecting and deſpiſing the Cenſures and publick Admonitions of the Church.</hi> In the Eccleſiaſtical Laws of <hi>Geneva</hi> p. 44, 45. <hi>They that do not obey the Orders of the Church after due Admonition, are order'd to be Excommunicated.</hi> If we look into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſee <hi>Conſtit. Eccleſ. Scot. cap. de Offenſis. A ſmall Offence or Calumny may juſtly deſerve Excommunication, if the Offender be ſtubborn and contumacious.</hi> 1 Book of Diſcipl. 9. Head. <hi>All Families muſt appear once a Year before the Preſbyter to be examined; and if Children or Servants be ſuffered to continue in wilful Ignorance they muſt be Excommunicated,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere their Excommunication is, appears from the 7th Head. No Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may have any converſe with him that is Excommunicated, not Eat nor Drink with him, nor Buy nor Sell with him, nor Salute nor Speak to him; his Children born after the Sentence, may not be admitted to Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. And I muſt ſay the contempt is the greater, when the occaſion of it is ſo ſmall. Lay aſide ſevere Penalties for Contempt, and Eccleſiaſtical Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction is loſt; and to what purpoſe ſhould any Court have a Power to determine, if there be no power given it to force the Execution of it? If we look upon Foreign Churches, we ſhall find that they are more ſtrict in having their Canons and Conſtitutions obſerv'd, than we are in <hi>England.</hi> I will not mention the Severities of the Scotch-Kirk,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62742:26"/> and <hi>New-Englands</hi> Diſcipline, as not being reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, nor ſuited to the Nature of the Thing; but in ſo plain a Caſe, let <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> the two great Apoſtles of <hi>Geneva</hi> ſpeak for all. <hi>Calvins Inſtit. l. 4. c. 5. ſect. 10. Let no one that deſpiſeth the Authority of the Church go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed, much leſs let any Body be permitted to break the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church; Chriſt looks upon ſuch as Deſerters and Runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado's; a ſeparation from a Church of God, is a renouncing of Chriſt; nor can there be any greater Crime.</hi> Again in his Comment on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Its eaſy to prove that Eccleſiaſtical Canons ought not to be accounted for Humane Traditions, ſince they are founded in the Word of God, and have a manifeſt approbation from the Mouth of Chriſt.</hi> Beza in Epiſt. 1. <hi>Shall we ſay that Men ought to have Liberty of Conſcience! In no wife, as this Liberty is underſtood, that every one ſhould Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God as he pleaſeth, for this is a meer Diabolical Opinion to let every one periſh that will; its a Diabolical Liberty which hath filled</hi> Poland <hi>and</hi> Tranſylvania <hi>with ſo many He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies.</hi> And again, the ſame <hi>Beza</hi> in his Epiſtle 24. to ſome Diſſenters in <hi>England. Things in their own Nature indifferent change their Nature when they are commanded, or forbidden by any lawful Authority—Laws about Things indifferent bind the Conſcience, ſo that no one can wilfully break them without Sin.</hi> To him agree the Dutch Divines in <hi>Synopſ. Pur. Theol. p.</hi> 453. <hi>No Body can wilfully diſobey the Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions about indifferent Things without Sin.</hi> But becauſe this is a Matter ſo very evident, I ſhall only add that in the Directory made by the Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines at <hi>Weſtminſter, p.</hi> 9. its expreſly declared, <hi>That no Perſons ſhould abſent themſelves from the Publick Ordinances upon pretence of Private Meetings.</hi> And the Words of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his Reaſons of the Chriſtian Religion, p. 485. <hi>No Chriſtian muſt pretend Holineſs againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace—And every tender Conſcience ſhould be as tender of Church-Diviſions and Real Schiſm, as of Drunkenneſs, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or ſuch other enormous Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We come next to conſider the great Point of Orders,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62742:26"/> and which ſeems to have been principally aimed at, <hi>viz.</hi> The allowing of Presbyterian Orders as valid, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Letter from the Country, p. 10, 11. <hi>propoſeth three Expedients, The firſt is Biſhop</hi> Bramballs; <hi>The ſecond is Hypothetical; The third is that of the Bill of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> To the firſt, I anſwer that Biſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi> did never allow of Presbyterian Ordination, but did actually, and with all the Rites and Methods of our Church, re-ordain ſuch as had been only ordained by Presbyters, as is evident from that very Place in the Life of Biſhop <hi>Bramhall,</hi> from whence this Author quotes a Paſſage, and what he did for Peace Sake was only this; That in ſome of their Certificates of their being ordained by him, he declared That <hi>this New Ordination did not deſtroy their former Orders, if they had any,</hi> &amp;c. And its abundantly evidently, that that Biſhop did re-ordain many of them. To the laſt of theſe three ways I return no Anſwer, becauſe he himſelf doth not tell us what it was that was propoſed in the Bill of Union. The ſecond was the principal Method inſiſted on, and that is Hypothetical Re-ordination, in which the Office of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination was to be omitted, and the Perſon kneeling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Biſhop, the Biſhop was to ſay, <hi>If thou art not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready Ordained, I Ordain thee;</hi> or elſe in theſe Words, <hi>I pray God that thou be ordained,</hi> &amp;c. And this is juſtified by the Inſtance of <hi>Hypothetical Baptiſm.</hi> To all which I reply,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Presbyterians (the Perſons we are to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy) have already declared againſt Hypothetical Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo the Presbyterians at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> in their Petition for Peace, p. 2. <hi>We earneſtly beſeech you that Re-ordination whether Abſolute or Hypothetical, be not made neceſſary for the future Exerciſe of our Miniſtry:</hi> now to grant them what they have already declared againſt, is no probable way to the Union pretented.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hypothetical Baptiſm is of Two ſorts, 1 <hi>ſt.</hi> When 'tis not known that the Child hath had any pretended Baptiſm with Water in the name of the Trinity, and then the caſe is not the ſame as this: Of ſuch hypothetical Rebaptization
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62742:27"/> the <hi>5th</hi> Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> c. 3. is to be underſtood, where they commend the Words of <hi>Leo, Iteratum dici non poteſt quod neſcitur eſſ factum,</hi> i. e. <hi>That cannot be ſaid to be repeated, which was never known to be done.</hi> The <hi>2d</hi> is, when all that hath been done is exactly known, but the authority of the Perſons Baptizing or Authenticalneſs of what is done, is called in queſtion; and in this caſe the Presbyterians do not allow of Hypothetical Baptiſm; witneſs the <hi>Synopſ. pur. Theol.</hi> p. 617, <hi>Neque Baptiſmus conditionalis probandus eſt, qui a Pontificiis obſervari ſolet,</hi> i. e. <hi>neither do we approve of Hypotheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Baptiſm which is uſed by the Papiſts;</hi> for they to gain reſpect to their own Church, endeavour to perſwade ſuch other Chriſtians as are admitted into their Church, to be hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetically Rebaptized; of which we have one famous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the Church of the Abyſſines, reported by <hi>Ludol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus in Hiſt. Aethiop.</hi> l. 3. c. 6. <hi>Patres Societatis Habeſſinos omnes promiſcue rebaptizaverunt, ſub conditione tamen, ſi videlicet prior Baptiſmus non rite fuiſſet peractus, quae res magnam illis invidiam conflavit;</hi> i. e. <hi>The Jeſuites rebaptized all the Habeſſines, with this condition, namely, if their former Baptiſm was not rightly performed, which thing occaſioned great troubles againſt them:</hi> Which troubles he reports, <hi>cap. 13. The Habeſſines hated them for nothing more than their repeating of their Baptiſm, as if before that they had been Heathens and Publicans.</hi> And is it not evident that Hypothetical Re-ordination will produce the ſame troubles here, when by this very Act our Church plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſeth that they were not ordained before?</p>
            <p>But to make all this matter plain, I will firſt ſet down the opinion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterians; then the opinion of the Foreign Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For our Engliſh Presbyterians. <hi>T. C.</hi> the Ringleader of that Party having been ordained by a Biſhop, is ſaid to have renounced his orders, and taken new orders from Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters in <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Presbyterians reordained Mr. <hi>John Cuningham,</hi> formerly ordained Prieſt by the Biſhop of <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loway. Ravil. rediv.</hi> p. 29. A whole Synod of the Puritans at <hi>Coventry, A. D. 1588, June</hi> 10, condemned <hi>Ordination by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops as unlawful; and farther declared the very calling of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62742:27"/> unlawful.</hi> Bancroft's <hi>Engl. Scotizing.</hi> p. 86. <hi>T. C.</hi> in his Admonition, <hi>p.</hi> 127, deſires <hi>the Biſhops to be laid aſide from ordaining Miniſters, and to bring in the true Election by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</hi> And in his Prayer before his Sermon at <hi>Banbury,</hi> printed in the Life of Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> p. 47. <hi>O Lord give us grace and power all as one Man, to ſet our ſelves againſt the Biſhops:</hi> Apologetical Narrative. <hi>Its a ſin to take Epiſcopal Orders, or to own the Authority of Biſhops.</hi> And to mention no more; in the Solemn League and Covenant, the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians of both Nations ſwore <hi>to the Extirpation of Prelacy, i. e.</hi> the government of the Church by Biſhops. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Presbyterians have generally perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all thoſe that had Epiſcopal Ordination.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Foreign Reformed Churches, obſerve, <hi>1ſit,</hi> That the Churches of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> are governed by Two Archbiſhops, and Fourteen Biſhops. The Churches of <hi>Swedeland</hi> are governed by One Archbiſhop and Six Biſhops; the Churches of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> are governed by Biſhops, the Reformed Churches of <hi>Bohemia</hi> have a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Biſhops as we in <hi>England:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſs we next to the Reformed Churches of <hi>Germany,</hi> which are in effect governed by Biſhops, whom they call Superintendants. Their Office is deſcribed in the Harmony of Confeſs. <hi>p. 227. to viſit Parochial Miniſters, to preſide in Synods, to examine and ordain Perſons fit for the Miniſtry,</hi> &amp;c. To which agreeth <hi>Carpzovins Juriſp. Eccl. l. 1. Comenius in Annot. ad rat. diſc. fratr. Bohem.</hi> where he obſerves that St. <hi>Hierom</hi> calls a Biſhop Superintendant; in <hi>Armenia</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is called <hi>Martabet,</hi> which ſignifieth Superintendant, ſaith <hi>Rycaut</hi> Hiſt. of Arm. Churches, <hi>p.</hi> 392. And <hi>Zanchy</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the Proteſtants have Biſhops and Archbiſhops, but that inſtead of good Greek Names, they call them by bad Latine ones Superintendants, and general Superintendants.</hi> And when in the Book of Policy <hi>(A. D.</hi> 1581.) for the Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Office of Superintendants is deſcribed; it is in theſe Words.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62742:28"/> Imprimis, <hi>The Superintendant of</hi> Orkney, <hi>his Dioceſs ſhall be the Iſles of</hi> Orkney, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Superintendant of</hi> Roſſe, <hi>his Dioceſs ſhall be</hi> Roſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Superintendant of</hi> Edenbrough, <hi>his Dioceſs ſhall be,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Superintendant of</hi> Glaſcow, <hi>his Dioceſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In all Ten Superintendants for that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Then follows the Function and Power of the Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant,—<hi>He ſhall plant and erect Churches, order and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Miniſters, Viſit,</hi> &amp;c. See the Proceedings at <hi>Perth, p.</hi> 14, 15. And in all ſuch Churches, where they have Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendants, there is no Ordination allowed but by them.</p>
            <p>An Account of the Perſecuted in <hi>Scotland, p. 58. There is not a falſer Propoſition in the World, than that the Inclinations of the generality of the People in</hi> Scotland <hi>are againſt Epiſcopacy,—and let us have a Poll for it when they will, and you ſhall quickly ſee the Demonſtration.—Of the Vulgus, the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty not a Third Man throughout the whole Kingdom is a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian.—And of Perſons of better Quality and Education, not a Thirteenth.—In all the Country on the North of</hi> Tay, <hi>thre never was above Three or Four Meeting-Houſes, and theſe too very little frequented. At</hi> Perth, <hi>where a Presbyterian Miniſter hath got the Church, not One in Ten go to hear him, not one of the Magiſtrates. The like at</hi> Cowpar <hi>in</hi> Fife, <hi>at st.</hi> Andrews, Sterling, Burnt-Iſland, <hi>&amp;c. Even in</hi> Edenbrough, <hi>the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Miniſters are not ſo much frequented as the Regular Clergy;—Whatever Friends the Presbyterians there had a Year or Two agoe, they arethis day diminiſhed by a Third; the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have enough of their Cant, and are weary of their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe Reformed Churches that are not governed by Biſhops, earneſtly deſire them. To this purpoſe, the <hi>Scottiſh Forbs</hi> in his <hi>Irenicum,</hi> Printed <hi>A. D. 1629, p.</hi> 202, hath theſe Words. <hi>Such was the condition of Proteſtants in many Foreign Parts, that being forced by utmoſt neceſſity, they allowed Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ordain; they heartily wiſh'd that they might be ordained</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62742:28"/> 
               <hi>by Biſhops, but when they could not obtain that of the Biſhops without wicked conditions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nor could the prohibition of Popiſh Biſhops hinder their Ordination from being valid, ſince in thoſe Countries the Presbyters and Paſtors had the chief power over the Chriſtian</hi> i. e. <hi>Reformed Churches.</hi> This they did, not out of any contempt of the antient Canons, but out of abſolute neceſſity, as appears from the Apology of the Proteſtants for the Conſeſſion at <hi>Ausburg, Art. 14. We have often te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified that we earneſtly deſire to retain the ancient Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Politie, and degrees in the Church, but the Biſhops,</hi> (i. e. Popiſh,) <hi>compel our Prieſts to renounce their Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Wherefore in ſome Places this Politie is deſtroyed, which we hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deſired to keep,—this we declare before God and the World, that it ſhould not be imputed to us, that we have no Biſhops.</hi> When at the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> an Engliſh Biſhop had ſet forth the uſefulneſs of being governed by Biſhops, for repreſſing He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy and Schiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Preſident of the Synod made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Nos non ſamus adeo felices,</hi> i. e. <hi>We are not ſo happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Moulin</hi> in his Preface to his Fathers Anſwer to <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> tells us, <hi>that the want of Biſhops in the</hi> French <hi>Church was the neceſſity of their condition, that they deſire the ſame Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we have in</hi> England, <hi>if they might be ſo happy.—When they moved Cardinal</hi> Richlieu <hi>to allow them Biſhops, he flatly denied it them;—They could never get of the Civil Power a toleration of Biſhops,—their Politick Stateſmen would never give way to it;—nothing hath been more eagerly oppoſed by the Pope and his Creatures, than that the Proteſtants ſhould have Biſhops.</hi> The Apology for Proteſtants, written by a <hi>French</hi> Divine, <hi>p. 60. This may ſuffice to ſatisfy the Scruples of thoſe that take offence at Epiſcopal Government, we have cleared the Point of Epiſcopacy,</hi>—p. 62. <hi>The Ordination of Prieſts ought to be without all diſpute the Biſhops work,</hi> p. 63. <hi>The Superiority of Biſhops to Paſtors has continued from the very time of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles or their Diſciples, as is already made appear.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>England</hi> the Papiſts have always laboured the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our Biſhops as zealouſly and heartily as the Presbyterians themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:62742:29"/>
            <p>That virulent Papiſt <hi>Sanders,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Schiſm. Angl. p.</hi> 167, confeſſeth, <hi>that nothing would more gratify the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>than the pulling down of Biſhops, Deans and Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries in</hi> England. And <hi>Parſons</hi> in his Book of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of <hi>England</hi> (ſee Moral Pract. of the Jeſ. <hi>p.</hi> 313,) propoſeth this as the neceſſary Method to bring <hi>England</hi> to the Romiſh Religion. And Cardinal <hi>Barbarini</hi> was ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of this, that he ſaid, <hi>he could be contented that there were none of their Prieſts in</hi> England, <hi>ſo there were no Biſhops.</hi> Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> Pref. to the Unreaſon. of Separation, <hi>p.</hi> 9. The Papiſts <hi>returned their Thanks to the Rump Parliament for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving delivered them from the Tyranny of the Biſhops.</hi> (Chriſtian Moderator, <hi>p.</hi> 32.) And that the <hi>Papiſts had a chief Hand in pulling down our Biſhops in</hi> England, is confeſſed by <hi>Albius</hi> in his <hi>Exegeſis,</hi> p. 145. If Papiſts may not be believed in this matter, I hope Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> may; and he declares in his <hi>Grotian</hi> Religion, <hi>p. 95. That the Papiſts had a Hand in caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out our Biſhops.</hi> I ſhall end this undoubted Truth with the words of Two Eminent Perſons of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Yelverton</hi> in his Preface, <hi>p. 9. It's now ſufficiently known,—what wonder the caſting out of Biſhops was to the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches abroad, and what publick Triumph to the Roman Conclave.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> in his firſt Preface to his Sermons, <hi>It's well known what rejoycing the Vote againſt Biſhops brought to the Romiſh Party, how in</hi> Rome <hi>itſelf they ſang their Io Paeans upon the Tidings of it, and ſaid Triumphantly, now is the day ours, now is the fatal blow given to the Proteſtant Religion in</hi> England. Upon which account, we have great reaſon to believe that the Romaniſts have uſed their utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to hinder the Reformed of <hi>France</hi> from having Biſhops as they heartily deſired.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us ſee what opinion the Eminent Divines of the Foreign Reformed Churches have of our Engliſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt. Calvin</hi> in his Book <hi>de neceſ. ref. If they will give us ſuch an Hierarchy in which the Biſhops do not refuſe to be ſubject to Chriſt, have him for their only head,</hi> (i. e.) in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62742:29"/> to the Pope) <hi>and be united to the truth of the Goſpel; then if there be any that do not reverence ſuch Biſhops, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to them, I confeſs there is no Anathema which they do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve;</hi> and in his Epiſtle to the Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> &amp;c. he commends our Engliſh Biſhops as ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2d.</hi> Bucer <hi>de Regno Chriſti. We ſee by the perpetual Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Church from the Apoſtles time, that it pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt to have one Perſon ſet over the Presbyters, to have the care of the Church and govern it, and therefore he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Biſhop.</hi> And again in his Works, <hi>p. 565. Theſe Orders of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons have ever been in the Church by the appointment of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And again in <hi>reſp. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. apud Goldaſt. Tom.</hi> 2. which <hi>Bucer</hi> was the Author of. <hi>How much miſchief the Reformed Churches have ſuffered for want of Biſhops, no one can eaſily find Words to expreſs.</hi> (Forbs <hi>p.</hi> 132.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3d.</hi> Beza <hi>in Ep. p.</hi> 18. Speaking of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, adds, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt appointed thoſe Orders.</hi> Contra Sarav. ad 518. <hi>Art. 3. If</hi> England <hi>continue to keep her Biſhops and Arch-Biſhops, let her enjoy that ſingular Bleſſing of God, which I wiſh they may always have.</hi> And again, <hi>(If there be any that reject all ſort of Epiſcopacy, God forbid that any but Mad Men ſhould joyn with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>4th.</hi> Spanheim <hi>in Epiſt. ad dub. Evang.</hi> Vol. 3. <hi>At</hi> Geneva <hi>they have a great eſteem for the Engliſh Biſhops, and daily pray for their Proſperity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>5th. Le Moyne</hi> from <hi>Leyden,</hi> publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet, p. 405. As for the Epiſcopal Government of</hi> England, <hi>what is there in it that is dangerous, or may alarm Mens Conſciences? and if this be capable to deprive us of Heaven, who is there that entred there for the ſpace of 1500 Years? for all that time, all the Churches in the World had no other Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>6th.</hi> When the Presbyterians had in their Solemn League and Covenant condemned Epiſcopacy, <hi>the Miniſters at</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renton, <hi>and of the other Reformed Churches in</hi> France, <hi>the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, Miniſters and Conſiſtory of</hi> Geneva, <hi>and other Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches in thoſe Part, were ſo ſcandalized, as that they</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:62742:30"/> 
               <hi>feared it would bring an indelible Scandal upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches,</hi> &amp;c. King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Large Declaration, <hi>p.</hi> 75.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When any of the Eminent Men of other Reformed Churches cenſured the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it was upon our being falſly repreſented to them. What <hi>Calvin</hi> wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Liturgy, was only upon the ſight of the firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>6th's</hi> Common-Prayer Book; and a Malicious Account he had received from ſome at <hi>Franck fort. Beza</hi> in his Letter to Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift, March</hi> 8. 1921. Declared, <hi>that in his Writings touching Church Government, he ever oppoſed the Romiſh Hierarchy, but never intended to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the Ecceſiaſtical Polity of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>nor to exact of them to frame themſelves after the pattern of our Presbyterial Diſciplene,—he wiſheth that the holy College of our Biſhops, may for ever continue and maintain their Right and Title in the Churches Government,</hi> &amp;c. And if <hi>Beza</hi> at any time wrote otherwiſe, <hi>he was abuſed by ſlanderous reports, which cauſed him to do it;</hi> ſaith Biſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi> in his Survey, <hi>p.</hi> 141. And his Gueſs we have confirmed by a Letter from <hi>Gualter</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> A. D. 1572. and Printed by Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift.—We admoniſhed your Adverſaries not to move any Contention in the Church for matters of ſo ſmall importance, and we thought the matter had been Buryed; when contrary to all Mens expectations, there came Two Engliſh Men from</hi> Geneva, <hi>and bring from Maſter</hi> Beza <hi>(whoſe Ears they had before filled with forged Accuſations, Letters full of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and deſire that we would help the afflicted State of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and adviſed me to make a Journey to you; to which was joyned the Report of theſe two, who reported the ſame things to us, that they had done at</hi> Geneva, <hi>and ſet down in Writing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Superſtitions which they ſaid were now defended in</hi> England;—<hi>but afterwards Letters from</hi> D. A. <hi>a ſingular honeſt Man delivered you all from blame.—Since that time we have had nothing to do with thoſe lying buſy-bodies, for not long after, it plainly appeared, that they went about, and were the chief Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of Diſturbances in the Palatinate Churches, and brought</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:62742:30"/> 
               <hi>much trouble and diſquiet to them. Wherefore I beſeech you, that you would not have any ill opinion of</hi> Gualter, <hi>who bears a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular affection to the Engliſh, and is perſwaded of our exact con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and agreement,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In our late Civil Wars, <hi>Milton,</hi> and <hi>Georgius Hornius</hi> (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Counterfeit Name of <hi>Honorius Reggius,)</hi> a Profeſſour at <hi>Leyden,</hi> and ſome others were hired to give a falſe and abuſive account of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to the Foreign Churches, and the very Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> wrote a Letter, which was ſent to the <hi>Belgick, French, Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetian</hi> and other Reformed Churches, to aſſure them, that the King made it his buſineſs to root out the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and uſed. all means poſſible to reduce the whole Nation to Popery. <hi>Bibl. Regia.</hi> p. 64. And of this we have as much reaſon to complain now as ever, it being noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly known, that not long ſince, a Gentleman of conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable quality made a Journey on purpoſe into <hi>France,</hi> to repreſent the Biſhops and Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as Popiſhly affected, it being the lot of this Church to be <hi>miſrepreſented</hi> by Men of Deſigns and Malice, for both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Fanaticks, as may beſt ſerve the turns of its Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in different Seaſons.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let us ſee what opinion the Univerſal Church hath of ſuch as in oppoſition to Biſhops, are ordained by Presbyters; the <hi>31ſt</hi> of thoſe that are called Apoſtles Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons. <hi>If any Presbyter deſpiſe his Biſhop, and ſet up ſeparate Meetings, let him be Depoſed, and the People Excommunicated.</hi> The <hi>5th</hi> Canon of the Council at <hi>Antioch</hi> decreed, <hi>that if any Presbyter deſpiſing his Biſhop, ſeparate himſelf from the Church, and make Meetings of his own; after the Firſt and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Admonition, he ought to be condemned, and not allowed to Preach, and if he ſtill go on to diſturb the Church, he ought to be puniſhed by the Secular Power, as a Seditious Perſon.</hi> This Canon is received into the Code of the Canons of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, and was confirmed in the <hi>4th</hi> general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> Act 4.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:62742:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his <hi>2d</hi> Apology tells us, that <hi>Coluthus</hi> a Presbyter paſſing by the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria, ordained ſeveral Perſons, all his Ordinations were declared void, and all that he had ordained, were reduced to the order of Laicks.</hi> And I want an inſtance of any one Reformed Church in the World, where Biſhops are eſtabliſhed, that Ordination by Presbyters in oppoſition to them, is allowed as valid; and I think the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the only Church in the World that being governed by Biſhops, allows of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Ordination, not regularly and of courſe, but by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary faculty from the Popes inexhauſtible Power. Of which, ſee <hi>Willet</hi> in <hi>Synopſi Papiſ. controv. 16. q 2. Theol. Rhem. in 1 Tim. 4. 14. Forbeſii Iren. p. 176, 177, 178, 179.</hi> where he largely proves it from the Canoniſts, Schoolmen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I am ſure the Papiſts have often objected it to us, that we have no Prieſts, becauſe we have no Biſhops, <hi>(Bancroft</hi>'s Survey, <hi>p.</hi> 166,) and have taken a great deal of Pains to ſet about the <hi>Nags-Head Fiction,</hi> and deſtroy the order of our Biſhops; which ſhews how glad they would be to have them all deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſuch Eminent Divines of the Foreign Churches that have come into <hi>England,</hi> and had only Ordination by Presbyters, and received Preferment here, have readily and willingly received Epiſcopal Ordination; and now it hath pleaſed God to ſend over ſo many <hi>French</hi> Miniſters into our Kingdom, I do not find but that they readily and chearfully comply with our preſent Eſtabliſhment in this particular alſo: From all which it's evident, that the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians will not comply with <hi>Hypothetical Reordination;</hi> that in moſt of the Proteſtant Churches, they are not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained but by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Superintendants;</hi> that where they have neither, they heartily wiſh for them and deſire them, and account Ordination by Presbyters in oppoſition to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to be Schiſmatical, and not allowed in any Proteſtant Church in the World; and by conſequence our doing it in <hi>England,</hi> cannot be a likely way <hi>to promote the Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Proteſtant Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:62742:31"/>
            <p>A ſet Form of Prayer was ſeriouſly oppoſed by the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> who <hi>p.</hi> 23. tells us, <hi>that ſerious God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is like to be extinguiſhed, if only Forms be allowed in the Church;</hi> and <hi>p. 55. The Abatement of Ceremonies, with the Excluſion of all Prayers, but what are Read will not ſatisfie us.</hi> The Author of a Letter to the Convocation, would have many of our Prayers and Services left to the diſcretion and choice of the Miniſter, <hi>p.</hi> 21, 22. And the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <hi>A. D. 1644,</hi> and 1648, ordained, <hi>That if any Perſon uſed the Common Prayer Book, he ſhall forfeit for the 1ſt Offence 5 l. for the 2d 10 l. and for the 3d Offence a Years Impriſonment;—and every Miniſter that ſhall not ſtrictly uſe the Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſhall forfeit the Sum of Forty Shillings; and whoever ſhall Preach, Write or Print againſt it, ſhall forfeit betwixt 5 l. and 50 l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Churches of <hi>Denmark, Swedeland, Saxony</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Ausburg</hi> Confeſſion, have their ſet Liturgies, and forms of publick Worſhip; yea the Churches of <hi>France, Geneva</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> have their ſet Prayers compoſed by <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf; as <hi>Luther</hi> compoſed Prayers for the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Churches, and <hi>Zuinglius</hi> for thoſe of <hi>Zurick.</hi> The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>Synopſ. pur. Theol. Diſp. 36. Sect. 33.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare <hi>ſet Forms not only lawful, but very profitable.—The attention of Auditours is much helped by having a conſtant form.</hi> Some of the Churches of <hi>Zealand</hi> thus declared themſelves to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterians, <hi>We account it grievous to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all thoſe Churches which from the Apoſtolical times, and the Primitive Church to this day have celebrated the publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, by preſcribed Forms;—wherefore we blame the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ſingularity of thoſe, who caſt out all Forms out of Divine Worſhip.—In almoſt all the Reformed Churches, Church-Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies, and Forms of Prayers are approved as profitable, and conducing to Edification. Capellus</hi> Profeſſour of <hi>Samurs</hi> in <hi>France,—in Theſes Salm. A ſet Form of Liturgy is highly uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and neceſſary,—hath been always uſed in all the Chriſtian Churches in the World for above 1300 Years, and now is uſed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62742:32"/> every where, except only by ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſtarts in</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Greek</hi> Church, <hi>Armenian, Coptick, Ethiopick,</hi> and all the Eaſtern Churches have ſet Forms of Prayer. <hi>Calvin. Epiſt. 87. I do very much approve of a ſet Form of Prayer and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Rites, that it be ſo certain, as that the Miniſters ſhall not recede from it,—that hereby the levity of ſome Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors may be hindred, there ought to be a ſet Form of Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf in his Def. of the Cure of Diviſions, <hi>p. 55. He that ſeparateth from all Churches amongſt us on the account of the unlawfulneſs of our Liturgy, doth ſeparate from them on a reaſon common to all, or almoſt all Chriſtian Churches upon Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Prayer before Sermon, <hi>Calvin</hi> conſtantly uſed the ſame <hi>Form</hi> faith <hi>Beza</hi> in his Life, it's Printed at begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Sermons on <hi>Job,</hi> ſo had St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> after Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. The Miniſters of <hi>France, Geneva</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> uſe a ſet Form before Sermon. <hi>Lavater</hi> of the Rites of the Church of <hi>Zurich</hi> ſaith, <hi>'Tis not the cuſtom of that Church for the Preacher to contrive new Forms of Prayer, and repeat them in the Publick Aſſemblies, but to keep the uſual one.</hi> And <hi>Durell</hi> tell us, <hi>that there is not one Miniſter in</hi> France <hi>but hath made to himſelf a ſet Form of Prayer, which he conſtantly uſeth before Sermon, and no other.</hi> So that in this alſo, our Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians are ſingular, that they affect Novelties and <hi>extempore</hi> Expreſſions and Variations in their Prayers before Sermons; I ſay that are ſingular, and different from the Paſtours of moſt of the Reformed Churches in the World.</p>
            <p>I know it's objected againſt our Liturgy, that it's taken out of the Maſs Book, as if the Lord's Prayer, the Creed, or other parts of our Service, were the worſe for being found there alſo; but yet thoſe that have ſtrictly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this, find the Objection falſe. <hi>L'Eſtrange</hi> in his Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 30. <hi>The beginning of our Morning-Prayer, Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Exhortations, Confeſſion, Abſolution, rehearſing the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are not to be found in the Maſs Book, nor any Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62742:32"/> Service.</hi> And Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> in Antiq. Br. ch. <hi>p. 232. All theſe parts are retained in the excellent Office of our Church; not from the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>(as our Diſſenters weakly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine,) but from the conſent of all the ancient Churches in the uſe of them,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>p. 237. From which diſcovery it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that our Church of</hi> England <hi>hath omitted none of thoſe Offices, wherein all the ancient Churches agreed, and that wherein the</hi> Brittiſh <hi>and</hi> Gallicane <hi>Churches differed from the</hi> Roman; <hi>our Church hath not followed the</hi> Roman, <hi>but the other, and therefore our Diſſenters do unreaſonably charge us with taking our Offices from the Church of</hi> Rome. And therefore the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> have ever been as zealous in oppoſing our Common-Prayer, as the Presbyterians themſelves; Mr. <hi>Harding, John Ould,</hi> and other Papiſts wrote Books againſt it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of our Martyrs were put to Death in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Dayss, for uſing the Book of Common-Prayer, ſaith <hi>Fox</hi> in <hi>Acts &amp; Mon.</hi> And the Author of <hi>Calvino Turciſmus,</hi> p. 360, hath theſe words. <hi>The</hi> Engliſh <hi>Liturgy, as to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it, is more corrupt than the</hi> Turkiſh <hi>Alcoran; as to the Form, it in great meaſure agreeth with it.</hi> And it's not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that the Papiſts would thus abuſe a Book that was ſo like to their own Maſs, as the Presbyterians would have it. Our Common-Prayer Book is now printed in Ten ſeveral Languages, which cannot be ſaid of any other Liturgy in the World; and ſo great was the eſteem our Forefathers had of it, that I find in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth, Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin</hi> and <hi>Thacker</hi> were both puniſhed for publiſhing <hi>Brown</hi>'s Book againſt the Common-Prayer. And now if all the Proteſtant Churches in the World have their ſet Liturgies, it muſt needs be a very improbable way to promote the Peace and Union of the Reformed Churches, by deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Liturgy we have always uſed.</p>
            <p>And to paſs by other things, moſt of the Reformed Churches have declared in their Confeſſions of Faith, that no Separation ought to be made for different Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, where there is an agreement in Doctrine. See
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62742:33"/> 
               <hi>Praef. ad Confeſſ. Helv. &amp; Art. 17. 27. Conf. Gallican. Art. 32. Bhoem. c. 15. Argent. c. 14. Auguſtana, Art. 7. Polon. p. 220. Calvin, Inſtit. l. 4. c. 10. ſ. 27. Is ſo far from condemning Rites and Ceremonies, that he would have them in every Church be fix'd and certain, without which the Nerves and Sinews of a Church will quickly be diſſolved,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>O Ecolampadius</hi> in his Epiſtles, p. 169, 177, 182, 184. <hi>Is vehement in preſſing every particular Church to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity in Ceremonies, that tho they are different in ſeveral Countries, yet all that are ſubject to the ſame Goverment ſhould be bound to the ſame Rites,</hi> &amp;c. And how little theſe eminent Reformers agree with our new Modellers, will appear from the Letter to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, p. 9. <hi>If any of the Laity ſcruple the Croſs in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, the Miniſter may be permitted to Baptize without it; or if kneeling at the Sacrament, the Perſon ſcrupling may have it delivered him in another Poſture, and ſo for God-fathers, p. 15. Let a Rubrick be inſerted before the Athanaſian Creed, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying that the Creed may be read, (or may be let alone) or with an</hi> alias, <hi>this or the Nicene, p. 21. Let the Litany be left to the diſcretion of the Miniſter to read or omit; let it be left to his diſcretion one day to read one part, and another day an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; that it be permitted in the Afternoon to leave out the firſt Leſſon, or the like, p. 22. That it be left to liberty and diſcretion to uſe the Prayers without the Leſſons, and the Litany alone on</hi> Wedneſdays <hi>and</hi> Fridays; ſo Preface to the Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry complain'd, <hi>that they were urged to read all the Prayers.</hi> And after this manner we muſt have nothing ſix'd and ſettled, but all our Rites and Prayers left indifferent, which is ſo far from promoting Union and Peace, that its the moſt likely way in the World to divide us, perpetuate and eſtabliſh Schiſm, and make us an caſie Prey to our Enemies: Even the Author of naked Truth, p. 23. ſaith, <hi>That a Liberty left to add or detract Ceremonies or Prayers according to the various Opinions and Humours of Men, will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly cauſe great Faction and Diviſion.</hi> Again, the length of our Liturgy is complain'd of—<hi>Letter to the Convoc. p. 18. It's propoſed, that the Sunday Service be ſhortned, p. 19.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62742:33"/> Its a tedious and prolix Service;</hi> which, tho it agreed with the complaints of the Presbyterians, <hi>A. D. 1603. Who then deſired the longſomneſs of the Service to be abridged;</hi> yet doth ſo little ſuit with our later long-winded Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, that at the <hi>Savoy, 1660. p. 9. They complain of the Brevity of the Common-Prayer-Book, and therefore deſire to have leave to pray more copiouſly—and p. 55. They complain'd of too many Prayers, not too much;</hi> ſo that ſhould we in complyance with this Projector, have ſhortned our Prayers; we ſhould have diſpleas'd, not ſweetned the Presbyterians to a Complyance. If we look upon the moſt eminent Proteſtant Princes that we have had, they were all for ſtrict Conformity. Queen <hi>Elizabeth would have the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>of all Men duly obſerv'd, without alteration of the leaſt Ceremony:</hi> Life of Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> p. 29. And King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt in his Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the firſt Year of his Reign, <hi>We admoniſh all Men that they ſhall not ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect, nor attempt any further alteration in the Common-Prayer—We are not ignorant of the Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that ariſe in Government, by admitting Innovations in things once ſettled by mature Delibaration, and how neceſſary it is to uſe Conſtancy—Such is the unquietneſs of ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſitions, affecting every Year new Forms.</hi> Our frequent al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations of our Religious Rites, hath been juſtly laugh'd at by Foreigners. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> for this very Thing derided the Engliſh in his time, and <hi>Cardan</hi> in <hi>Tetrab. c. 3. Tex. 12.</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the Engliſh are ſtill changing their Rites and Manners of Religious Worſhip, ſometimes to the better, and very often to the worſe.</hi> Not to mention what St. <hi>Auſtin, Epiſt. 118. adjan.</hi> obſerv'd, <hi>Ipſa mutatio conſuetudines etiam quae adjuvat utilitate, novitate perturbat,</hi> i. e. <hi>The very change of a Cuſtom, tho to the better, breeds a diſturbance by its novelty: Malum [politicum] bene poſitum non eſt movendum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſine, give me leave to repeat what the Ingenious <hi>Lord Faulkland</hi> long ſince told us, viz. That <hi>all <hi>Mutations</hi> are dangerous, even where what is introduced by that <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:62742:34"/> is ſuch as would have been very profitable upon a primary Foundation; and it is none of the leaſt Dangers of Change, that all the Perils and Inconveniences that it brings, cannot be foreſeen; and therefore ſuch as make Title to Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, will not undergo great Dangers, but for great Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities,</hi> ſuch as cannot, I preſume, be here preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Upon all which Accounts its evident that the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions complying to make the Alterations propoſed, is the moſt probable way to diſpleaſe moſt of the Foreign Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants that are now in League with us, and make us no longer eſteem'd, as we hitherto have been, the very Center of Union.</p>
            <p>I will add but one Reaſon why we ſhould not make theſe Alterations for the ſake of our own Diſſenters, and that is, becauſe they are reſolved they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have no Union with us; but whenſoever we are making Propoſals to unite with them, they run farther off, and be ſure make freſh Complaints of theſe very Changes, and ſteps towards them. For the Alterations made in 1660. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> likes things worſe than before, and hath declared frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Print, <hi>That many of our old Epiſcoparian Divines, had they been now alive, would have been Nonconformiſts, and that the new Impoſitions make the Miniſterial Conformity harder than formerly. Def. of Cure of Diviſ. p. 55.</hi> The Presbyterians at the <hi>Savoy</hi> (after p. 35.) <hi>complain of the paucity of Conceſſions,</hi> (tho lately ſaid to be 600) And again, <hi>In one of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, in which we ſuppoſe you intend to accommodate with us; you rather widen than heal the Breach.</hi> When about ten Years ſince, ſome of our Church had a project of Comprehenſion, the Presbyterians were farther off than before; and under the Name of a Plea for Peace, put out bitter Reflections upon the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet</hi> unreaſ. of Separat. Pref. p. 36. <hi>In</hi> Scotland <hi>the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians adminiſtred the Solemn League and Covenant to the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62742:34"/> People, and made them Swear never to hear the Orthodox Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry more, and gave them the Sacrament thereupon.</hi> Ravil. Rediv. p. 29. <hi>The like is ſaid to have been lately done at</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton, <hi>and ſome other Places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how have they behaved themſelves in this juncture, we may take it from one of the great Promoters of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, in his Letter for the Bill of Union, p. 4. <hi>I do own, that in ſome of the Diſſenters there is more then an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Averſion to this Bill of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, or elſe Books level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt Liturgy and Epiſcopacy would not come out as they do, in this p juncture, freſh from the Preſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Word, There are two Things that have formerly made the Government very averſe from favouring Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, 1. Their Diſloyalty. 2. Their readineſs upon all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to joyn with the Popiſh Intereſt againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as they famouſly did in the Year 1588. at the time of the Spaniſh Invaſion; and again 1688. in the late Reign of King <hi>James</hi> II. as appears from their nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Addreſſes; their Complyances with the Diſpenſing Power; their Promiſes to take off the Teſt and Penal Laws; their new Ordinations; and their great neglect both in Pulpit and Preſs, to defend the Articles of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, againſt the many Writings of the Papiſts; two Tracts only amongſt the numerous Diſſenters, having upon the ſevereſt computation, been found publiſh't by them, during the whole Reign of that King; we had great reaſon to hope that theſe Failings had been both mended, eſpecially at a time that Popery was diſcouraged, and the Government had been ſo kind to the Proteſtant Diſſenters; and yet behold quite contrary to all ſober Mens Expectations, tho there are but two Things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of all that are Hearers in Conventicles, in order to a full Toleration, 1. An Oath of Allegiance and Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to the King and Queen. 2. Making and ſubſcribing a Declaration againſt Popery, and ſo giving ſatisfaction to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62742:35"/> the Government in theſe two particulars, yet they are ſtill either ſo ſteddy to their old Principles of Diſloyalty, or ſo far managed by Popiſh Agents; and withal, ſo peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perverſe, and froward in oppoſing every thing that is commanded them by the Laws; that to this day, ſo far as I can learn, there is not one in an Hundred of them that hath done either.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62742:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
